<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Divine meditations.]</title>
            <author>Palfreyman, Thomas, d. 1589?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08848</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08848)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Divine meditations.]</title>
                  <author>Palfreyman, Thomas, d. 1589?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[23], 67 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Bynneman, for William Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC; imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Paulfreyman.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Diuine meditations.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20797:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the righte wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipful, Maiſtreſſe Iſabel Harington, one of the Gentlewomen of the Queenes Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Chamber, Thomas Paulfreyman hir dayly Orator wiſheth (with continuance) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Gods eternal grace and fauour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S EXPERIENCE playnely teacheth, tyme truely telleth, and nature for the moſte parte appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the diuerſitie of our humane affects in diet: hovv not only to the vvorshipful or moſt honorable, but alſo to the very poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and of moſt baſe eſtate, the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateſt, moſt deintie, ſvvete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant dishes, are not alvvayes aptely agreable, or to contente fully their minds, but ſometimes for a shift and to their better liking, deſireth more ordinarie, groſſe and familiar fare: vvherby in nature they are the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:20797:2"/>contented, their appetites ofte times more quickened, their minds recreated, yea, and the healthes of their bodies the better alſo preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: euen ſo (righte vvorshipfull) touching the interne parte, diuine ſubſtance or invvarde affections of the ſoule: the heauenly nature alſo and moſt chriſten diet therof, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and tyme beareth likevvyſe their ſvvay, effectually to iudge and declare the ſame in truth, among the ſounde members of Chryſtes onely immaculate, moſt preciouſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted body, to their ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation, quickning, recreating, and moſt healthfull preſeruing. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit you are herein for your part, as the electe of God ſurely grounded in him of good purpoſe foreap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, and by grace moſte hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely called, to be in this life (vvyth prepared ſoule and quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience)
<pb facs="tcp:20797:2"/>partaker of ſundry his heauenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates, accuſtomably norished, moſt dayntely ſedde, and abundauntly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied, to your very vvell lyking, in the excellencie of ſuch your ioyouſe and invvarde refection: and vvithout ouer ſecret hiding, a knovven diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butor of your good portion to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for their bothe bodily and ghoſtly comforte at all times in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, as the shevver fauourably foorth the flovving frutes of fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and true pietie: yet preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon your vertue and chriſten clemencie, I haue novve boldly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted and moſte humbly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto you (for varieties ſake) this moſte vnvvorthy, very ſlender, and ouer baſe preſent, to be at the leaſt by your godly ſufferaunce (as ſuperfluous ſtore amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the reſt) but a backeſtander in your ſight, to bee looked vpon aloofe, a long and farre
<pb facs="tcp:20797:3"/>off, as it vvere but by the vvay, euen vvith a glauncing eye, and at leiſure to be tryed for your onely pleaſure, vvhat is the effectuall and true taaſt therof. But not to alienate or alter by any meanes, your already vvel ſtaied and moſt happy affections, ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily confirmed in you (and that in the beſt parte) by the ineffable po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vver of Gods moſte ſacred ſpirite, your only and omniſufficient piller: but rather in dede to incitate you (if poſſibly it might be) to the better eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ovvn former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, and moſt faultleſſe fornamed furniture. And truely greate reaſon vvhy it should be ſo, that things vvel knovven, and of moſte excellencie, should haue condignely their beſte preferment: for ſo God him ſelfe vvith the moſt godly, vvould vvishe by iuſtice it should ſo be, hovv ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly they are knovvne
<pb facs="tcp:20797:3"/>to the contrarie. And notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the dayes are novve diuerſly daungerous, very dayntie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in muche fyneneſſe, vvhether in ſpeaking, curiouſe deuiſing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte ſearching or penning of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, touching either diuinitie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervvyſe of Prophane deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo very ſinguler, exquiſite, pycked, and tender are mens eares, naturally adioyned to their flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing, quicke, and ready vvyttes, profounde knovvledge and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente: and therefore the more ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſardefull, and a meane truely to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe vnto themſelues that deale in ſuche caſes, rather reprochefull and many ſcornefull ſcoffes, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation or shevv of good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, vnleſſe they rarely exceede or ſurmount the vvel dooings of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite others: and that alſo (touching thys my preſente attempt (vvheras
<pb facs="tcp:20797:4"/>the godly in theſe dayes, hath moſte gratiouſly endeuored to ſet forth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and that moſte plentifully, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſondry vvorks, very diuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of great excellency, and of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, to quicken and ſtirre vp daily to God, the ouer drouſie, ſlacke, &amp; ſick ſinnefull ſoules, to reioyce alſo their mindes, and to fructifie before him, their vnprofitable and baraine harts: yet as a pore helper, a moſt inferiour labourer, or vvell vvilling drudge in the vineyarde of Chriſte, humbling my ſelfe moſt gladly, vnder the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the charitable and frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the godly vviſe in their knovvn vertue and humbleneſſe, approued skilfulneſſe, vvatchfulneſſe, and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die diligence, in that their holy fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction appointed: beholding vvith them the neceſsity of the time, hovv the vvilde vveedes of vvilfulneſſe to vvickedneſſe, ſinne and abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:4"/>do daily abound and raign rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvithout ſufficient ſtoppe, in their very infectuous and filthie fulneſſe, to choke, to repreſſe and kepe lovve by the grounde, the fragraunte and ſvveete ſmelling fruites of vertue: vvhereby, as vvith infinite ſnares, the Diuell entangleth, ſtill daily encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, infecteth, poiſoneth, and hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all the leudly idle, careleſſe and vaine children of this ſo ſore crazed and old ſtouping vvorld of deth (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redie iudged, condemned, and at the brink of deth:) in vvhom, by vvhom, and during vvhoſe time, Satan temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, allureth, deceiueth, plucketh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes him, and toſſeth them as it ſeemeth vvith his cruell clavves, vp ſide dovvne at his pleaſure, and dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vvith them at his vvill, as vvith his ovvne poſſeſſed, as vvith thoſe that forſake God, as in a time of the contempt of god, of hating the clere
<pb facs="tcp:20797:5"/>light of god, of louing the darkneſſe of the diuel to their condempnation more than the light, of ſelfe loue, of pride and vanitie, of defiled life, and ſuche like: a time approued of all times, moſt ſtraunge, moſt monſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and therefore the more daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: vvherby ſathan vvith his vvhole rablement of hellike miniſters, the vvorld alſo it ſelfe, and the proud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious flesh, mainly beſtirreth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvith their full povver togither, to make hauock, &amp; to bring altogither vnder their ſeruile, moſt confuſed &amp; bitter yoke: I haue in my moſte ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnderſtanding, and as God therin by his grace hath directed me, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored to beſtovve ſome parte of my time, in ſetting forthe ſundry godly meditations and prayers, vpon ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cauſes reſpected, as inſtrumentes, to shrub, to roote out, cutte dovvne, ſpoile and deſtroy, at the leaſt ſome
<pb facs="tcp:20797:5"/>poyſoned euils, from the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful and louely vineyard of Chriſte. And as I haue by them thought moſt conuenient, that oure almightie and moſt terrible God (vvho ſeemeth to be greatly amongſt vs forgotten) in euery of them shuld cheefely be had in remembrance, to be duely reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and feared, to be called vpon and moſt highly magnified: ſo haue I for the moſt part, made mention of our frailetie, preſent and moſt vvretched ſtate, and of the mightie povver alſo of our forſaid enemies, hovv politike they are, hovv puiſſant, hovv vvatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, hovv cruel, hovv accuſtomably in all eſtates they do preuaile, and that God therfore by humble ſute vvold ſone graunt vs his mercy, exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forth his arme to ſtrengthen vs, and moſte grationſly in time deliuer vs: leaſt in the vvaightineſſe of our ſins yet daily amongſte vs encreaſed, vve be ouer
<pb facs="tcp:20797:6"/>ſore preſſed, oure conſciences moſte fovvly defiled, burdened, depely gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and vvounded, the iudgementes of the higheſt not vvayed, oure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard ſenſes benummed, oure hartes hardened, all diuine graces contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo vvith the plages of God, the more ſvviftly by his iuſtice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: heaping in the vvhile ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues, againſt the day of his vvrathe and publike declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of his proclaimed and iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to be dampned vvith the vvorld, vvith the Diuell, and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels for euer: vnto vvhom, by vvhoſe cuſtome, and importune knocking at the doores of our graceleſſe, very vaine, and moſt fruteleſſe hearts (the knocking of the Lorde Chriſt vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully neglected) vvee haue ſubiected oure ſelues, and opened vvide vnto him, to let in both him ſelf, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned companions, and vvith them
<pb facs="tcp:20797:6"/>all abhomination and vnrightuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte, to quicken vvith more haſt the flames of Gods furie, to make pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous and ouer heauie, the ſvvitfe deſcending ballance, of his very ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible &amp; irrcuokeable iuſtice. To the ende therefore, this ſmall and moſte ſimple volume, may (vnder youre godly protection) gather the rather ſome eſtimation and credite, &amp; paſſe forth for good to the vſe of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I moſte humbly beſeeche youre vvorship, ſo to accepte it in the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie thereof, and graunt thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Chriſtian furtherance, that ſome good for Goddes glory, may grovve thereby to ſome, that ſome liues at the leaſt may be ſomevvhat amended, the furies of God the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preuented, and the bright lighte of the ſonne of god shine with more povver amongſte vs, to ouerthrovve vs in his feare, to beate flatte to the
<pb facs="tcp:20797:7"/>earth, our carthie and proude fleshe, and to vvaſte ſoone or conſume, for good and moſt happie chaunge, our moſt damnable vvorks of darkneſſe. I shall (as of bounden duetie, for this and for other the like cauſes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) moſt humbly pray for you, that God in mercie may euer bleſſe, both you, your moſte vvorthy belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Chriſte, your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, and vvhole familie.</p>
            <p>Your humble and daily Oratoure, THOMAS Paulfreyman.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20797:7"/>
            <head>An exhortation to the chriſten Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing mindful (de uout christian) of god thine heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father: and as best beſeemeth thee, an earthly creature, always to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy maker, &amp; that by a quickning ſpirite in the inwarde and newe man, commended vnto thee from aboue, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the free grace of election in Ieſus Christ: by whom thou art new borne: to whom thou art coupled a quick and a lyuely member: with whom thou art partaker of the Heauenly and diuine nature: (euen the nature of God thine eternall father:) In whom thine harte is prepared towardes him: by whome thou ſeekest most truly to knowe him:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:8"/>most earnestly to loue him:<note place="margin">Whervnto the eternal ſpirite ſtirreth the hearts of gods electe.</note> diligently to ſeeke him: faythfully to ſerue hym: moſt lowly to honour him: reuerently to feare and obey him: and ſo foorth as his only worde of truth moſt ſtraightly preſcribeth and preciſely requireth of thee, of all people, and in all eſtates, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all generations. In his hygh magnificence, almightyneſſe, etermtie, great power and maiestie: to loue him in his benignitie, in his myldeneſſe, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, faithfulneſſe, truth and greate mercie: to feare him in his lordly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, princely gouernment, ſtatelineſſe, rough countenance, wrathefulneſſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iuſtice and iudgement: and to offer daily vnto him, the acceptable ſacrifice of faithfull and hartie prayers, in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Christe, as hee himſelfe most healthfully taughte thee: and for whoſe onely ſake, promyſe is made to heare thee, that his myghtye hande may ener preſerue thee, vphold
<pb facs="tcp:20797:8"/>thee, keepe thee ſafe, noriſhe thee, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte, ſtrengthen, defende and deliuer thee, in all places, at all tymes, and in al caſes of neceſſitie, bothe of bodge and ſoule: and to giue thee alſo thorough Christ, his holy ſpirite, as a ſeale of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, to certifie thee that thou arte the chyld of God, inwardly to inflame and comforte thee, to warke true faith into thee, to dispoſe with cherefulneſſe the frutes of true charitie, to quiet thee in al tempests of aduerſitie: yea and to leade thee ſtill on by the hande (for the tyme, and from time to tyme) vnto the place of reſt, the cheerefull and ſafe porte, the restfull hauen or moſte ſure rode of eternalioy and felicitie. If thou deſire to enioy all theſe and ſuche lyke bleſſings as are moste needefull for thee (both for body and ſoul) from the hand of God, and according to the meaſure of the gift of Christ: O hearken then vnto the voyce of the Lord thy God:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:9"/>Incline bubly thine eare:<note place="margin">A preparation to Prayer.</note> prepare thine hart: ſike him early in holineſſe: turne thee vnto him without delay: receyue him with most pure affection: and lift vp ſone thy ſickely ſoule, to beholde the glory of his countenaunce. O bond thy body of earth, downe to the face of the earthe. Grone in thy ſelfe to God with greefe, and lay open ſimply before him, the felt ſecretes of thy ſinful hart. Call daily vppon him, and ſo aduiſedly trie him, as thou haſt aſſured truſt in him. And before thou duetifully at tempteſt thy godly contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, prayers, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and thanks giuing to God: prepare thee earnestly a ſitte ſoule, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence of ſo high and great a God.<note place="margin">Certaine ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial cautes fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, that are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidied by gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the ſelues before prayer and receyning of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramintes, to auoid his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</note> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not before whome thou preſentest thy ſelfe, and vnto whome thou doste minde to talke. Be not vainly or wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly preſumptuous, in thine high and great attempt before him. Abaſe thy ſelfe: tremble in his preſence. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:9"/>god beholdeth al diſorders in thee, with a piercing, ſharpe, and reuenging eye.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Examine therfore thy ſelfe before with indgemente. Deſcende deepely into thine owne bowells, and ſee there, whether thou be (as of ryghte thou oughtest) truely penitent for thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinnes and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether thou determineſt (thence forth) from thine hearte, not to tourne againe vnto them, as dothe a cleane waſhed ſwine, which newly defiles hir ſelfe, in the lothſome and foule ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mire.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether thou bee in his ſighte a louble faced or deepe diſſembling hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, touching thy dealings with him and the worlde, as thy booke in thee of records moste playnely witneſſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether thou bee (as by name thou profeſſest) a zelouſe fauorer of
<pb facs="tcp:20797:10"/>the word of life.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether thou (with the Prophet Dauid) vnſeinedly hatest all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiouſe vanities, contrary to the word of life.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Whether thou (with the ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete) feelest in thy ſelfe to be grieued with the enemies of God, and with all ſuch as riſe vp ageinst him, or to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the word of life.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether thou weyest wyth thy ſelfe, that like as thy body, being but of an earthy and corporall ſubstaunce, cannot poſſiblie liue without the vſual nouriſhmente of materiall bread and meate: ſo the ſoule, in the ſpirituall ſtate therof, cannot liue but be ſterued and dye (euen the eternall and euerlasting deathe) withoute the ſpirituall nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and heauenly ſweete tast of the woorde of God, whiche to the ſoule is the onely breade of lyſe, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after thou ſhouldest hunger, too vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb facs="tcp:20797:10"/>thy lyfe.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether thou ſtedfaſtly beleue to be ſaued, by the only merites, death and bloudſhed of Chriſt crucified vpon the croſſe, withoute thyne owne and other mens merites, eyther their most dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and idolatrous deuiſed vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Whether thou thynkest it not the Dyuels bewytchyng, by his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne mimſters, to bee depriued of ſo pious and precious a prepared raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether thou at the receyuing of the holy mysteries of Chriſtes body and bloud, vnderſtandest them to bee his owne only ordinance, for the vſe of his holy churche, and to bee witneſſes therein of the open and publike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true ſaithe whiche thou haste in him, and to be ſaued onely by his bodilye death and the bloudy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vppon the Croſſe, once for all
<pb facs="tcp:20797:11"/>offered vnto God his heauenly father, for thine, for mine, &amp; for al the ſinnes of the whole worlde, euen ſo many, as haue this acceptable ſaithe of God in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>11</hi> Whether thou haue regarded by the word of God (touching the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Christes body and bloud) the difference therin, betwixt the Diuelles faith and thine, either the ſaithe of an Hipocritiſhe and dampnable repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>12</hi> Whether thou haſt by true ſaithe repugned the Deuill,<note place="margin">The diffrence to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red betweene the true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians fayth, the faith of the diuell, and the reprobate</note> who boldely chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth thee (as he thinketh he may be bolde) and maketh equall compart ſon with thee of thy ſaithe, touching ſimplie the confeſſion of Chriſte, as of his Conception by the holy Ghoſt: of his Natiuitie and birth of the virgine Marie: to be alſo the Sonne of God liued perfecte and vndefiled man vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earthe, his doings to be onely
<pb facs="tcp:20797:11"/>omnipotent, moſt miraculous &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: ſuffered moſt ſharpe and cruell death: was buryed: roſe againe, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the heauens, verie God and very man: yea, and of his retourne alſo againe vnto iudgement. All theſe things, the Diuels beleeue and confeſſe with thee: but yet vtterly vnperſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to be his onely ſufficient ſauioure and redeemer, by his precious bloude ſhedde and deathe: euen as thoſe ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wickedneſſe, which in theyr vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe, ſtubborneſſe, &amp; vnſtayed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, touching the couenant of God in his ſonne Christe, for their ſaluation, accompt the price of his precious bloud to be inſafficient for them, withoute the very abſurde and most fond annexing of their owne and other mennes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites: and ſo to make Christe vnto them ſelues, to be at the moste, but a mingled, peeced, botched, and patched Sauioure.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20797:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>13</hi> Whether thou hast on this maner folowing conſidered of Sathans cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge and compariſon with thee, and ſayde thus vnto hym in the ſecrecies of thy faithfull ſoule,<note place="margin">The true chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at earneſt defiance with the diuel: and ſhe weth vnto him for his diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>geme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the power of his fayth.</note> for thy defence: O thou very mortal, moſt cruel and dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned enemie, I vnfaynedly from myne hart defie thee: I withſtande thee to the face: thou hast naught to doo with me, or to make ſuche compariſous with mee in my chriſten and moſt holy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion. I know full wel thy malice and ſtoutneſſe, which hath ben in thee from the beginning, bothe agaynſte the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted of God and all his. Experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce teacheth me, of thy not ſlumbring, of thy wandring about, and ſeeking wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chefully to deuoure and to ſpoyle mee of my faith, wherby I must be ſaued. I tell thee thou moſt wicked one, thy tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell is all in vayn. I am none of thyne, nor nothing inclined to thyne affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or motions. I am Gods I tell thee,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:12"/>and the perſwaded childe of God by his ſpirit of truth, who by grace poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing me, and by his power mightily working in mee, hath moste graciouſly planted in my harte, the frutefull tree of pictie, of true and perfect fayth, faſt roted in me, deply ſtayed, and ſurely ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, euen with the finger of god my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, touching the dignitie, price and true estimation of his ſonne, and mine onely ſauiours most preciouſe body, for mine only health and eternal ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And though I haue falne or fainted, as traiterouſly thou hast tripped me, yet of frailtie haue J falne, &amp; not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of malice, as thou haste most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly tempted me: which God hath ſeene in me, in mercy therfore hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me vp ageyne, and wil ſtil vpholde me in ſpite of thee. Art thou ignorant of this (thou griſeled and foule helly monster) that I am not ſuch a one as thou art, or as thou woldest haue mee,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:13"/>to bee doubtefull of my faythe, as the wicked are, to leaue the freedome of Gods ſpirite, and to bee entangled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in thine infernall filthy bands? Thinkest thou, that I beeyng nowe called to the lighte and knowledge of the ſweete woorde of life, whereof I haue truely taſted, and haue in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation mine olde conuerſation, will be newly agayne deceiued, offer to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, eyther once nibble or ſmell to thy beſlubbered, brackiſhe, and most filthy embrued baytes? Notest thou me of ſuche ſlipperineſſe, that ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng farre entraunce in the ſpirite, and feele the incomparable ioyes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, that I will nowe ende in the greefes and ſorrowes of the fleſhe? to ſette ſo lyttle by the Kyngdome of Ieſus Chryste, that taking holde of the Plough, will now looke backe agayne, to bee as a Dogge, and to returne agayne to my vomite, or as a beaste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:20797:13"/>Swyne, to beraye my ſelfe agayne in the myre, to defourme the Image of God, and to defile his holy Temple? No no Sathan thou arte deceiued, I tell thee truely for thy diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, I am now better ſchooled, well armed, and better warned, to let thee goe for naughte. Knowest thou not that I haue put vppon me to endure for euer, my Lorde and God, my Chryſte and Sauioure? Art thou forgetfull (O thou enemie) that I in true faythe profeſſing his name, and receyuing woorthily hys bolye and most bleſſed Sacraments, by the onely rule of his word, am armed ouer all, with his only healthful, and most mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull merites, to ſtrengthen me mighti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ageinst thee: who is made mine with all that he hathe: and I am onely hys, hoth body and ſoule: one bodye wyth him: fleſhe of his fleſhe, and bone of his bones. Ah Sathan, this certeinty and
<pb facs="tcp:20797:14"/>truth in faith conſidered, wastefull are thy wretched wandringes and wylye waightings to wreck and vex my ſoul. Away from me, away J ſay thou curſed and ſpightfull ſpirite: or ſtay if thou lust to offer boldly vnto mee (as thou darest) thy very blaſhleſſe and bragge attempts of malignitie. I yet tell thee, they ſhall not hurt me: neither do I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing esteeme thee: J regard not thy force: J feare not thy fury: The Lorde is my God: he is the God of my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and conſidence: thou hast of thy ſelfe, no powre at all ageinst me: For what ſo euer thou attempteste or ſeekest to performe, therin to thy wil thou wantest powre. But that which thou doest, is by his onely omnipotent hande and ſufferaunce that is my God: whoſe waight and mightineſſe, thy brooſed braines hath ſelte, to make thee ſtonpe for euer, to hamper thee at his will to thine owne irons, to ouer throwe thee
<pb facs="tcp:20797:14"/>ſoone in thine owne tourne, and to blowe thee backewarde at will, euen with the breath of his mouth, into the baileſſe and deepe botomeleſſe pitte: whoſe bonde ſlaue thou art and a drudge en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced: and in thine outrage by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, a knowne peereleſſe paricide, a very restleſſe, pitileſſe, and most grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe raunging roge, the only ring lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and infectuouſe ranke roote of all reproch, of all miſchieues and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation vnder the ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>14</hi> O beloued Christian: Whether art thou in this wiſe armed with ſaith too ſtande too the face of the Diuell, ſharply to reproue him, and put him to flighte?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>15</hi> Whether haſt thou in thine harte through this ſaith, heauenly mirth and melody, inward reioicing, and thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne with triumphe, exalted the name of thy God, felt in thy ſelfe to bee doubtleſſe his childe, and too loue (as
<pb facs="tcp:20797:15"/>thou lawfully oughtest) the lawe of thy deare and most louing father?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>16</hi> Whether hast thou conſidered or not, this heauenly mistery aforeſaid to be the Sacramente of true pietie, the Character of perfecte vnttie, and the most aſſured band of frutful and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charitie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>17.</hi> Whether thou, being a ſubiecte in any estate (borne to be ruled vnder thy ſoueragne and not to rule) bearest vnto hir thy dere and natural Prince as alſo to thine natiue countrey (by the bloud of Goddes woorde) a naturall, ſaithfull, and true louing harte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>18</hi> And finally, whether thou bee christianly charitable, or a cleere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitter of all thy neighbours offences as thou thy ſelfe woldest of God be clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remitted. And ſo foorth in all other thinges, as best behoueth thine holye profeſſion: least to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary (in gods ſighte) all thy conceyued holineſſe by
<pb facs="tcp:20797:15"/>orater or whatſoeuer, beeing but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vbane, hipocritiſh, childiſh, mere dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and very folly, there be founde in thee, but the only title, or vnauailable bare name of christianitie: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore verie perniciouſe, burifull, and to be tourned into ſinne ageinst thee: and ſo in ſtead of healthfull, very delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and beautifull bleſſings (which thou daily huntest after) the banefull, most bitter, and blacke curſes of God, doo ſodeinly fall vppon thee. Beware then J exhorte thee, looke well to thy ſelfe: in time: flatter not thy ſelfe vainly or rather dampnablie: be not longe a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, in the ſchoole houſe of daliaunce: be not alwayes a fondling, a weakling, or a ſuckling, a milkeſoppe, or babiſh infante in Chryst: weye truely the vertue of healthefull, manfull, and ſtrong nouriſhmente in Chryste, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to the tyme: thou ſhouldeste nowe bee a ſtrong man in Chryste:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:16"/>thou art now as a man most grationſly viſited, for the highest doo ſeeke thy company: than the which, what ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest thou more deſire. O remember then, how very reprochfull, how vnma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnhealthfull, hurtfull, miſerable, and diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, is thy ſeruile ſtate, in ſuch wiſe to be pind in, not to growe out in time, nor get from thy rockinges, thy weariſome wrappinges, or ſwad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling bandes of extreame weakeneſſe: but alwayes to be lulde in the armes of vntimely tenderneſſe, wherby thou art barred from thy highest and moste chiefe ſolicitie. Way warely by the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, thy due danger and diſcomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, of ſuche thine inſenſibilitie and weariſhneſſe. Shouldeſt not thou rather reioice, to be calde as a man of ſtrength to the felowſhip, ripe age, and ſtrong manhode of Christe, and to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker in his preſence, of his most frende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, healthfull, ſtrengthfull, and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:20797:16"/>banket? whereunto, al things are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prepared, and therunto art thou now called. God alſo graunt thee, to be in the number of his electe, that thou maist with ſaith ſet forwards thy fote, hungerly with zeale to ſtriue for thy place, &amp; to beleue by Gods only word, that the lord of the ſeaſt fauoreth thee. Be not hindred, hinder not thy ſelfe, let excuſes be farre from thee, deferre not the fauouring of thy ſoules refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, loke to thy turne in time, open to day thine eyes, and be not yet blinde to morowe, least with the blinde, in thy wil of blindeneſſe, thou be ſone blindely led, into the irrecouerable, deepe, and most damnable dungeon of blindneſſe, darkneſſe &amp; horror, with the diuel, the Prince of darkneſſe and death foreuer. Conſider this, he that ſeeth thee (euen as in deede thou art) is a God of moſte cleare ſighte, bright lighte, truthe and rightuouſneſſe. Call to minde towardes
<pb facs="tcp:20797:17"/>him, thy true profeſſion &amp; ſeruice: turn not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but of true kinde: leane ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> truthe: ioyne not with the wicke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which by their queſtions dout of that truth, and aske how knowe you that it is the word of truth: for bothe they &amp; thou ſhall anſwer to that word of truthe: whereby must be directed, bothe thy religion and manners: and wherin, thou muſt be bothe mindefull, skilful and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keful for thy diſcharge. Jgnoraunce cannot excuſe thee, it ſhall not excuſe thee: thou oughtest not be ignorant, thou nedeſt not be ignorant: what ſo euer is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy learning: thou readest it, thou hearest it, or thou maist if thou luſte: It is not farre from thee: It is before thine eyes &amp; in thine hart, if grace be with thee towardes it, and is moſt truely pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto thee, by the eternall ſpirite of truth, &amp; that moſt miraculouſly with al ſimplicitie, by his zealous ministers, inwardly to pierce thee, to lighten the
<pb facs="tcp:20797:17"/>darkneſſe of thine hart, and to quicken true life vnto thee, if thou haste eares to heare in theſe dayes, the dayes of gods grace, and of his heauenly viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Vaine curioſitie of faultes finding and complaining, ſhal not ſerue thee, in thy reſpecting of perſones, dayes and times: they oughte not to hinder thee: haue thou thine hart prepared, &amp; ſtick thou to the graces of god offered. What are ſlanderous brutes to thee, if thou be of god &amp; a louer of the truth: of which truthe, let thine owne conſcience be the iudge, if it be not vtterly dead, or most damnably benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou hearest the truth, in time take hold of truthe, let not occaſion ſlip from thee, with hir turned baldneſſe towardes thee: for ſhee flieth ſwiftly, and to cal hir again back wil not help thee: yea, the truth wil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reproue thie, be iuste iudge ouer thee, and condempne thee to thy face, for thy moſte foliſhe and late repentaunce
<pb facs="tcp:20797:18"/>Jf truthe therefore offer hir ſelfe vnto thee, ſtand most amiably before thee, and ſound most heauenly words vnto thine eare: O attend then to the truth, haue good opinion in the truth, ſlie not from the truthe, feare not the truthe ioyne to the truth, be familiar with the truth, beleue the truthe, confeſſe boldly the truthe, and ſtand ſtedfastly to the truth: for truthe is of high excellencie a glorious ladie, a dame of noble fame and of great antiquitie: ſhe is euer gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious vnto the frendly, of full power al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo, of great maiestie, and familiar with the highest. Thinke well therefore of truth, entertaine hir reuerently, ſhee ſhineth with glory vnto thee. O let hir alwayes poſſeſſe thee, reioyce in hir co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panie, and vſe hir very frendly, for ſhe wil highly againe requite thee, &amp; ſhen thee ſone moſt freely, hir natural vſage &amp; propertie: which ſhalbe, all inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to ſerch thee, thorowly to purge thee
<pb facs="tcp:20797:18"/>most clerely to polliſh thee, moſt beuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to adorne thee to breake thy ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of impietie, to make the ſpiritually free and prefer thee, through true ſaithe to poſſeſſe the high preſence of the deitie. This is truthes nature, to deale kindly with thee, if thou most vnkindly, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectest not hir companie. Of whiche truth, the Apoſtle thus wryteth vnto thee, that without al contradiction ſhe muſt nedes be vnto thee, either the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of life vnto life: or the ſauoure of death vnto death. Such iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t will truth haue ouer thee, and ſtand in full effect, there will be no meane, but to be either with thee, or elſe flatly againste thee, as it ſhall truely finde thee, at thy fal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this life. there wil be no dalia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: it will for euer ſaue thee, or eternally damne thee, how ſo euer thereof thou makest thine account, or leanst of will to the contrary, with thy very blinde, wicked, and peruerſe hart. Feare ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:19"/>harken to the truth in time, haue ſure confidence in truthe, thine helper is at hand, be and the truth are one, he is grateful, he is faithful, dout thou not double not, nor wilfully withſtand not, the offred graces of thy mylde master, thy iust Lord, and moste louing God: and be not before him, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his holy Angels, vnprepared, or a dallier, a man indifferent, a ſlacke Simme, a drouſie one, a lyngrer, a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deaier, a wanton, or a careleſſe one, among the reiectes and wretches of this worlde: that in their coldeneſſe, darkeneſſe, hopeleſſe houeryng, vayne deuiſing, wilfulneſſe, tolitie, forgeiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, contempte of God and Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, tempteth ſo hygh, ſo magnificent, terrible &amp; great God of maieſtie, moſt deadlily to danger them, elues: who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly in a moment, and in the twin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling of an eye, is able by his iuſtice to destroy thee, to cracke ſodainely in
<pb facs="tcp:20797:19"/>ſunder the thred of thy life, &amp; to twine ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly the cordes of thy perdurable &amp; eternal death. Therfore as he ought, in his mightineſſe, of euery wighte to be feared: ſo he ſhold not of any one, either preſumptuouſly or vainely be tempted. But for thy part, obey him in his will, and ſuffer him with all pacience, to try thee through aduerſitie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting thy ſelfe wholely vnto his only wil &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: for ſurely he will (beholding in thee the power of ſaithe) not ſuffer thee to be tempted aboue thy ſtrengthe, or yeelde thee ſo farre to fall, but with his owne right hand, will raiſe thee quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vp againe. And I exhorte thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to take heede, that thou poſſeſſe not in his ſight at any time, an vnſtayed, ofte wauering, and winde ſhaken hart, through Sathans bluſtrings, ſtormie and tempestuous blastes, ſtirred vppe daily and hourely againste thee, and that by Goddes permiſſion for good:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:20"/>least by thine impaciencie, diffidente trembling, and ſore ſhakes of thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſten inconſtancie, thou be ſodainly turned to thy ſhiftes, put to thy faultie flight, and ſo be diſpoſſeſſed of thy verie healthful, ſafe, and moſt ſure holde: or elſe ſpoiled with reproche of thy chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten armor: or be occaſioned by despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate purſute, to ſtarte from the face of the ennimie, to ſtacker fearfully at his offered blowes, and in hazarde to take hurt by ſome dangerous and ſodain fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greatly to diſhonor thee before Chriſte thy captaine: and with him infinite armies of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſoldiors: whoſe tents (to encourage thee) are pitched round about thee. I ſay therefore vnto thee (O Chriſtian) ſtand thou cherefully to thy charge in all things, and defende manfully thine owne: diſmaie thee not J ſay: for the Lorde God him ſelfe will be thy defender and keeper, and wil ſtand by thee to ſtrengthen thee,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:20"/>and to deliuer thee from all daungers. And if legions of diuels ſhould copaſſe thee, trench thee in round about, plant their power, and be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forcibly their ſhot agaynst thee: well may they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly thunder far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, rore, rattle and rumble in the aire ouer thee, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble terribly about thee, parche ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thy tender skin, and wonderfully in ſuch ſort amaſe thee: yet ſhall they not preuayle agaynst thee, hurte any member of thee, or once remoue thy faſt fixed ſoote, but ſhalt ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſure fer euer, euen as the highe, mightie, ſteadie, and ſtrong mounte Sion: for Gods arme ſtayeth thee, who by his power hathe ouercome the diuell, euen the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell Sathanas him ſelfe, he holdeth him at will by his infernall chaynes, his whole curſed armie alſo, hell gates, and al the powers of hell. O praiſe therfore thine almightie God: exalt his glorious name for euermore, watche and pray
<pb facs="tcp:20797:21"/>continually: pray with vndersta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, pray at al times, and in al places, as his holy ſpirite ſhall moue thee, for the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of thee, and for the auoyding of the engins, ſleights, and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations of the enimies: that God himſelfe may be pleaſed, thy ſoule ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthned, the diuels chaſed, va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed, or put to flight. And when thou prayest, deceiue not vaynly thy ſelfe: be not blinded with the proud Phariſie in thine owne conceite, boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of thy righteouſneſſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, neither glorying in any thing: for he throughly beholdeth thee, and ſeeth that truely in thee, euen thy ſecrete and hidde ſinnes (a maſſe of all abhomination) as thou oughtest chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly therein to be thine owne iudge. But humble thy ſelf before him, with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent and poore wretched Publicane, confeſſing thy ſinnes and wickedneſſe: and feare not then to attayne grace, through ſuche true faith &amp; hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:20797:21"/>Moreouer, forget not, that as God is a moste highe, heauenly and diuine ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and a ſpirite of al goodneſſe and truth: ſo wil he alſo of thee be ſpiritually worſhipped, prayſed, and prayed vnto, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the truth, by the word of truth, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the depth and bocome of thine hart. This alſo I put thee in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of (a thing greatly requiſite) that in the tyme of thy prayers, which thou daily conſecrateſt to god (be they more or leſſe, long or ſhort) thou be not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen with the ſnarling ſuggeſtions, ſecret twitches, inward motions, or wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſleightes of the enimie Sathan, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the abuſe of thy ſenſes and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde bodily members, as thine eyes, thine eares, and ſuche like: that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest thy tongue onely oft babbleth, and vaynely wastest muche breath: thine hearte, whiche God chiefely respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth, and dothe very gladly deſire, bee fardest off, and bee moste vaynely
<pb facs="tcp:20797:22"/>turned another way, gretly to diſpleaſe him, to vexe ſore thine owne conſcience, and to make vtterly frustrate al thine attempts, or importune ſutes of greate neceſſitie. This I ſay alſo vnto thee: If thou deſire to be the child of God, and voyde of al doubts ſo in dede to be, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy hart Christ thy forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſauiour, by whoſe onely grace thou arte adopted the childe of God. Make not towards him, thy fidelitie, craſed, mingled, or patched: let it goe ſoundly and al whole togither, both fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy body &amp; thy ſoule. Let him alwayes enioy fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee the whole &amp; perfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the man regenerate &amp; new borne, and made by his ſpirit the child of light, ful of agilitie and liuelineſſe: whoſe ſoule mounting with felicitie ſtill vp to the heauens, is there reſident with Chryst the ſauiour, and alwayes conuerſant in heauenly things. And let him alſo bee euermore vnto thee, thine onely, whole,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:22"/>ful, perfect, and ſufficient redemer, ear nest petitioner and ready pacifier of the diuine fury against thee for al cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: who with great glory (as thou ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt confeſſe) is aſcended on high, and ſitteth with almightineſſe, power and maiestie, on the right hand of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, with open and freſh blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wounds (the many fest marks &amp; impreſſions before him for euer) of the purchaſed &amp; most preciouſe redeemed inheritance, euen for thee, moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and deadly ſinner, by the ſecrete testimonie of thine owne conſcience. Theſe things &amp; ſuch like, of thee thus christenly conſidered, thou mayest bee bold with thy moſt merciful and louing God. But yet agayne I ſay vnto thee, hold thee ſure vnto thy ſauiour christ, ſwarue not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, nor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vertue of his onely merites, wherby thou must be onely ſaued. Cleaue then cloſe to the rocke of aſſurance: leane to no looſe nor
<pb facs="tcp:20797:23"/>ſandie ſafetie. Trust not to the rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our humane deuiſes, labour not to languiſh in a maze of vncertaintie. Bemoyle not thy ſelfe in ſuche myre of mortalitie, and ſhun ſoone ſuch ſhoures as wil wrecke thy ſoules fidelitie. Then cry (as J ſayd) and ceaſſe not to craue pardon of God thy father in his ſonne: name, 'Doubte not of thy ſute, what ſo euer it be, for it ſhal by good motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſo vpright, ſo reaſonable, ſo acceptable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him and allowable: and ſhal touch therwith ſo neere the tenderneſſe of his mercy, his truthe and fidelitie, that of neceſſitie graunt muste bee made vnto thee: he wil not denie thee the requests of thy lippes: yea, he will ſo graciouſly tender thee, that foreſeing thy cauſe of inwarde complaynte, he wyll pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare quickely thine heart moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to call vpon him. Beleeue therfore faithfully, trust of aſſurance, and thou ſhalte ſurely obteine thy deſire, with
<pb facs="tcp:20797:23"/>greate mercy and fanour at his holy hande. Thy ſinnes ſhal not be imputed vnto thee, thou ſhalte bee bleſſed and righteouſe in the ſighte of God all the dayes of thy life, ſo happily ſhall thine hart be prepared: ſo mightily ſhal thy prayers preuayle for thee: they will forcibly pearce the celeſtiall and high heauens: approche neare to the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throne of grace and maieſtie: cry inceſſantly for thee, &amp; will not returne from the preſence of God, nor once be ſatisfied, before the full graunt of their humble ſute, for thy ſauing health and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie. To conclude in all thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attemptes, whether in praying, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, geuing of Almes, frequenting the holy Sacramentes, or rendering moste hartie thankes vnto God, for his infinite Mercies, Graces, Bleſſinges and Benefites bestowed vppon thee, and vppon his whole Churche, from the beginning vntill this preſent day:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:24"/>and what ſoeuer in holineſſe thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendest daily vnto him: let it always be done vprightly, orderly, with chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian comelyneſſe, and modestie, with peace of conſcience, faithfully, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cherefully, and in charity, as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde of God moste ſtraitely byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee. Which I pray to God may clerely ſhine into thee by the power of his holy ſpirite: who quicken thee this day, to morow, and for euer, and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in thee towardes him, the firie flames of his true loue, throughe his ſonne Chryst Ieſus: who ſpeedely graunt thee the ſame ſignement of his holy hand, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee with inward ioy, in all thy moste lowefull and diuine deſires. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20797:24"/>
            <head>A deuout meditation of the godly Chriſtian, with a briefe Confeſsion and Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I (O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) thorowe the glorie of thine only eternal gracs am eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of many mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, lamentable mournings, déepe ſighings, and inwarde monings to my ſelf, moſt happily ſtirred to the due conſideration of my ſelf, and in what perillous ſtate I euer ſtande here in this wretched worlde, how in the breuity therof I am compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with many miſeries, with gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous plagues and puniſhmentes, with dreadful calamities, perilles, and dangers, with diuers maladies ſickneſſes aand infirmities bothe of
<pb facs="tcp:20797:25"/>body and mind:<note place="margin">The mercy &amp; grace of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the hearts of his elect, to coſider in this life their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate for ſinne.</note> how by the mighty power alſo &amp; pollicie of mine anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and moſt deadly enimy the olde ſubtile ſerpent, this deceitful vaine world, as alſo mine own weaknes, corruption, apte inclination, &amp; moſt vile ſubiection to ſinne, I am daily aſſaulted and tempted to ſinne, and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting ſinne, become the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of ſin, &amp; muſt acordingly looke for death the iuſte reward of ſinne: bicauſe diuerſly therwith and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably (through diſobedience &amp; the breach of thy law, in thought, word and déede) I haue and do moſt grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offend the will of thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and am become thereby a very Sathaniſt, the childe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, to haſten thy furies vpon mée, that he ſhuld vſe his tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie againſt me (for ſo witneſſeth by accuſation my wounded conſcience,) whereby my ſoule is daylie dyſquieted, ſore
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20797:25"/>clogged, gretly deſtled, maruelouſly amaſed, made monſtruouſe before thée, and hated of thée: wherevnto (my freedom and innocencie being loſt) of my owne concupiſcence am accuſtomably blinded,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice therof.</note> drawne and entiſed: and by the malice thereof, both vnderſtanding, heart and wil are holden captiue and in deadelie ſlauery to the diuel,<note place="margin">The diuell the onely author of concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and ſin.</note> the only author and beginner of all euell concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and ſinne. By which occaſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in ſtead of healthſome and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinges, I ofte deſire very noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, moſt pernitious and hurtfull things. And my ſoule alſo which in the excellencie therof, through rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and the vprightneſſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, ſhould beare the beauty of thy heauenly and moſt glorious ymage in perfect puritie and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, through the corruption ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſowly deformed and ſore ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:26"/>and made accordingly his euill fauoured &amp; moſt filthy image,<note place="margin">The ſoules de formitie tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ſinne.</note> and ſo woorthily by thy iuſtice ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, and caſte from the preſence of thy deitie.<note place="margin">True faith in the abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding mercies of God.</note> So that héereby (O Lord) thou haſt yet by the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thy grace moued me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that if thy mercies did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde vppon me, or that thy grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fauoure, ſhould nowe or at any time, in this moſt deadly plight vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake me, and not rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably with ſpéedy and moſt ſwift ſway turne againe towardes me, and bring therwith from thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly preſence, the diſtilling moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and large flowing ſtreames of thy celeſtiall dewe, plentifully drawne from the ſwéete fountains of my ſauioure, to refreſh, comfort, make whole againe, clenſe &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, my very leprous, moſte ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſicke ſoule, and of thy méere
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20797:26"/>mercie to reduce hir to hir priſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate &amp; former ſtate:<note place="margin">The miſerable ſtate of the ſicke Soule, without true faith in the fre mercy of god.</note> my caſe ſhould be moſt miſerable, my bands ſhuld be indiſſoluble, I ſhoulde become a curſed reiect, &amp; remain a fire brand of hell for euer. But as thy loue (O Lord) is vnſpeakeable, and thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly mercie toward me infinite, which willeſt not the deathe of a ſinner, but rather he ſhould fourne from his wickedneſſe and liue, and offreſt him time and ſpace to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and amende:<note place="margin">The feeling of the grace of god.</note> ſo haſte thou now in mercie remembred me, looked back againe vpon me, cheared and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me, encreaſed true faithe in me, thy ſpirit hath renued me, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me to call moſte humbly vnto thée, ſet me frée from the ennemie, pitied my ſoules deformitie, prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the moſt healthful remedie: for the bloud of thy ſonne Ieſus hathe clenſed me, whereby thou haſte ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20797:27"/>quickened me, that my ſoule reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth within me,<note place="margin">The humble ſubmiſſion &amp; confeſſion of the faythfull Soule.</note> with moſt earneſt teares it repenteth me that euer I ſinued againſt thée, I fall flat to the earthe before thée, confeſſing my ſinnes vnfainedly, my weakeneſſe and infirmitie, for I haue moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offended thée, my conſcience therein accuſeth me, &amp; crie yet with true ſaithe vnto thée: Mercie good Lord mercie, with thankes giuing and extolling thée, for thine infuſed grace vppon me.<note place="margin">A calling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for comfort and ſtrength.</note> And I pray thée moſte humblie (O my God of all mercie) to continue thy fatherly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the encreaſing of thy grace, and ſtrength of thy ſpirit vpon me, to helpe, to directe and comfort me, vnto the ende, and in the ende in all my temptations, troubles, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and infirmities bothe of bodie and minde: Leaſt ſathan (as I ſaid) preuaile and confound me, the tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20797:27"/>pleaſures of this world deceiue me, and the olde man my wretched fleſh, which is not yet ſubiect to the ſpirite, do maſter me:<note place="margin">The fighte of the faythfull Soule.</note> againſte all which, I muſt arme my ſelf, ſtande to the battaile, continually fighte, bolde out at the ſwoordes pointe, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the pricke, driue backe, chaſe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe, wound and confounde, whileſt breath ſhall holde in this wretched body: yea, I ſay wretched in déede, being compaſſed with ſo many calamities and infinite miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: for the which cauſe, (O Lord) I craue alwayes thy mightie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in my weakeneſſe I make my mone, haſte thée nowe to helpe me, O ſtrengthen me, graunte me thy preſence, ſtande by me, encourage me to fight manfully, that by thee I may amaze the enemies, put them faſt to flight, gette the victorie, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe before thée, and extoll thée
<pb facs="tcp:20797:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>in thy great might &amp; mercie, nowe and for euer: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: who liueth and raigneth with thée and the holy Ghoſt in all honoure and glory worlde without ende. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. To dvvell in the ſeruice of God, to haue the world, and the pleaſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, and to ſtriue daily againſt them with the armor of rightuouſneſse.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as muche (O al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God) as we are all warned by thine holye Apoſtle Iohn, not to bée lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thys euyll world, nor the vain pleaſures ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, bicauſe bothe the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come vtterly to naughte: and that alſo to be a louer of the world,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20797:28"/>is to be an hater of thée,<note place="margin">What danger they fall into that forſake god, and leane to the worlde and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof.</note> to ſlip from thy will, and from the preſence of thy maieſtie, as one that regardeth thée not, knowes thée not, neither ſéeke to know thée, but ſtartle aſide from thée, forſaketh the right way, and entreth of will the perrillous way full of hidde thiſtles, thornes, briers, brambles, venemous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſerpentes: linking alſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues into the amitie, league and ſeruice, of the moſte ſleightie, hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and deadly enemie, the proude Prince of this worlde, who for a time by Gods permiſſion is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſe, and rageth in his courſe, roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and fighteth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually againſt the Soule of man: who entangleth only his owne to their vtter ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, with the vaine pleaſures thereof: euen with the delightes in effect but of one houre, and with the encreaſing of ſorowes for manye
<pb facs="tcp:20797:29"/>yéeres:<note place="margin">The ſeruice of God, what it is.</note> I beſéeche thée (O thou king of all holineſſe) whoſe ſeruice is moſt highe, moſt happie, moſt ſure, moſt healthfull, wealthful, heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perpetuall, perfecte ſelicitie and freedome:) which ſeeſt the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, inconſtancie, greate miſerie, and neceſſitie of me thine humble ſeruaunt: the outrage alſo &amp; power of my cruel aduerſaries: graunt me ſufficiencie of thy grace, &amp; ſtrengthe of thine holy ſpirite, that by vertue thereof, I may be directed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way wherin I ſhould walke, my pathes made ſtraite, and my foote ſtedfaſt, alwayes to withſtande the euil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes of the moſte wicked, and the outwarde glittering gloryes of this ſinful and vain world, and not yéelde my minde to the pleaſures &amp; comforts of the ſame, as a childe of vanitie, encloſed therin for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, as in a deepe dungeon of daunger,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20797:29"/>and of deadly darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">The worlde, a deepe donge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherin the children of vanitie are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed.</note> founded vppon a ſandie and rotten ſoile, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry olde, ruinous, ſore ſhaken, and readie at euery momente to fall, throughe age vppon me: but to be otherwiſe ſtaide by thine holy and mightye arme, pacientlie in the meane ſeaſon to abide thy will, to lay my foundation ſure, to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and watchfull ouer all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to ſtretch forth mine handes to the battaile, to ſtrengthen mine armes like a bow of ſtéele, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy protection &amp; power, I may manfully reſiſt all hurtful euilles, and the aſſaults of the wicked, and ſtand ſtably to my profeſſion in thy holy ſeruice, wherunto thorow thy grace I am called, to the ende, that by thine only helpe, I ſhould do the workes of rightuouſneſſe. O thou rightuous Lorde and God of my ſtrengthe, which haſte made me,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:30"/>which haſt conſerued me, and arte moſte louing and carefull ouer me, I putting mine only hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence (not in the holy Angels, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall ſpirites, bleſſed Sainctes in heauen, or good men héere in earth) but only in thée, ſuffer me not to be tempted aboue my ſtrengthe, or to be ouerwhelmed of mine owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: but in the midſt of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, make thou a way for me to eſcape with ioy. Thou (O God) art only omnipotent, moſte gratious, ful of al goodneſſe, faithfulneſſe and truthe: fulfil therfore thy promiſſes towardes me, moſt merciful Lord, thou God of truthe: Put vppon me thine whole armor of rightuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Armoure of rightuouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> O thou God of mighte and true holineſſe, that by thy power I may be ſtrong againſt all aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: for I wreſtle not (as thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt) againſt fleſh and blud in this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20797:30"/>life: but againſt rule, againſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and againſte worldly rulers of the darkneſſe of this worlde, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte ſpirituall wickedneſſe in heauenly things: by whome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thine heauenly power I ſtande euer in hazarde to eternall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction bothe of body and ſoule. For which cauſe (I ſay) O my ſwéete God, arme me ſtrongly, ſtrengthen me in my weakeneſſe, and make me ſtoute, that in this chriſten chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrie,<note place="margin">Chriſtian chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualrie.</note> I may ſtand perfecte in all things before thée, and not ſlippe by cowardiſe or inconſtancie from thy faithful ſeruice: but fight vnder thy banner vntil the laſt breath,<note place="margin">The ſight of a chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the ſeruice of god muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and couragious.</note> coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly putting mine euemyes to flight, and cary away with triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph, a glorious victorie ouer them. So ſhall it come to paſſe, that thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly running this ſo ſhorfe a race in my holy calling as a puiſſant war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
<pb facs="tcp:20797:31"/>in thy moſt high and excellent ſeruice, with lawfull ſtriuing, and with violent plucking towards me thine heauenly kingdome, I ſhall in the ende perfectly ſée it and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe it, and ſhall receiue in mine hands a Palme of victorie,<note place="margin">Palone of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie. Crowne of glorie. Hid Manna. And a White ſtone.</note> vppon mine head, a Crowne of glory pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, the hidde Manna alſo and a white ſtone, wherein is written a newe name, which no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſauing only the receiuer of it: who ſhal ſerue thée thou great God of heauen, in the moſte ſacred ſtate of true holineſſe, perfecte frée dome, excellencie, dignitie, and equalitie with thine holy Angels and al bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saincts, in euerlaſting felicitie. Graunt this mine humble petition (O Lorde) for thy greate mercies ſake: So ſhall I here, and in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſſedneſſe, extoll and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy glorious name. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20797:31"/>
               <head>III. For the humble hearing, apte recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing, keeping, and continuing of the vvoorde of God amongſt vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering (o thou God of al holineſſe) that the certainetie of oure Chriſtian faithe, ſtandeth by the Scryptures or immoueable woorde of thy truthe: which, as thy meſſenger procéedeth from thee by thy gratious inſpiration or ſecreate brething: wherunto, as vnto a ſeaſt royal, euery man of al nations vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen are called:<note place="margin">The ſcriptures of God, only receyued of the faithfull.</note> but are of thy Church only receiued and deuoutly vſed, to the inſtruction, confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtrengthening and eſtabliſhing of thine only faithfull &amp; true flocke: and be, as thy bleſſed Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, ſacred and holy: birauſe they be heauenly, moſte precious,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:32"/>diuine, healthfull, and comfortable to the ſoule, excelling all the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Philoſophers, and the vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe of this world, and be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in their high power and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie) woorthily aboue all aduanced, ſegregate, and put aparte by them ſelues, from all other wrytings of prophane matters and the flitting deſcriptions of men: not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to this preſent worlde, and for the vſe of this temporal life: but alſo from all Ethnicke ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">Superſtitions, falſe worſhip pings. &amp;c.</note> ſalſe woorſhippings, wicked ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and erronious opinions, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed contrary to thy woord, &amp; againſt thée the only eternal and true God: which, by lying, cuſtome and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, are corruptly crepte into thy Church, to the foule féeding, filling, defiling, and poiſonning therof, and is yet daily occaſioned therby wout thy grace, to be ſiniſterly drawne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20797:32"/>and ſeduced, ſtraying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the right way, and haled to death by will in oure ſelues, from the life that is in thée, euen to eternall death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: we beſéeche thée moſte humbly (O thou gracious God) to enſpire vs with thy holy ſpirite of truthe, &amp; to kindle in all our hartes the fire of thy loue, light and truth: that by thy power in them, oure faithes may be ſtrengthened, oure ſoules alſo humbled, rightly ledde and inſtructed, in thy word of loue, light, truthe, and of eternall life: by vertue wherof,<note place="margin">Our profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> at our firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to Chriſt our high Paſtor, we may truely vnderſtande our profeſſion and promiſſe in holy baptiſme, and haue it accordingly wrytten with thy finger of grace in our hartes, to the true knowledge of thy law, and the ſpiritual vnderſtanding therof, to loue thée moſte woorthily aboue
<pb facs="tcp:20797:33"/>all, and our neighbor as our ſelues: as alſo to knowe the promiſſes of thy mercie in thy ſonne oure Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt moſt ſoundly and purely, as thy holy word expreſſeth therein: whereby we may be well vpholden, and zealouſly ſtaide in our profeſſion, to treade our pathes right, to be guided by the true light, to heare gladly the voice of oure ſhepheard Ieſus Chriſte, to teſtifie his name, to folowe him the onely true lighte, and not to feare the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of darkneſſe, but to ouercome them by thy mighte (although euen with the loſſe of our liues) not only the dalyings, dimme deuiſes and vanities of the wicked, and to ſhun all ſuche hatefull enemics,<note place="margin">Enemies of Gods word.</note> as are vſuall mockers, daily deprauers, ſinnefull deſpiſers, wilfull impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, wicked ſeducers, double dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, backe ſliders, &amp; pluckers back
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20797:33"/>from thy word, but alſo the ſleights of their father Sathan, the entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the worlde, and the filthie motions of the fleſhe. And to that happie ende (O Lorde) we may be conſtant, and thy woorde euer abide in vs, ſtirre vs vp to continuall and hartie prayer, quicken our zeale,<note place="margin">Hartie prayer to God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante in the word of God.</note> &amp; woorke in vs, a true, liuely, quicke, and frutefull faithe: that it being a bright ſhining light in our hartes, to the expelling of all Hipocriſie, cloudineſſe, darkneſſe and erroure, and alſo our conuerſation being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to our profeſſion, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of thy grace may ſtil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably ſhine vppon vs, thy holy woorde may continue amongſte vs, may be truely preached vnto vs, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, boldly, and zealouſly vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ouer al, and by al the miniſters thereof, by what occaſion, time and place ſo euer it be: for vnto vs that
<pb facs="tcp:20797:34"/>ſhall be ſaued,<note place="margin">The worde of God, what it is, and how of the godly to be conſidted.</note> it is a thing moſte precious and holy: It is the woorde of life, the woorde of reconciliation, the lanterne vnto oure féete, and a light vnto our pathes, the fountaine of wiſedome, the breade of life, the foode of the ſoule, thy mightie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſwoorde of the ſpirite. And for as much (O heauenly father) as thy woordes thus to vswarde (come from heauen) are ſpirite and life, and are not to be wayed with the vaine imagination, policie, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or witte of man, nor yet to be applied vnto the hurtfull pleaſures of this ſinnefull worlde, but to be moſte holily and highly eſtéemed, moſte humbly had in credite, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently thought vppon, gladly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto, heard with ſilence, and receiued with all modeſtie &amp; ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gréedineſſe: we humbly beſéeche thée, that as thou haſte euer heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20797:34"/>ben the only gratious director, inſtructor and teacher of thy holy Patriarks and Prophets,<note place="margin">God the only inſtructour of all, in all ages.</note> Apoſtles and holy fathers from time to time from the beginning, and amongſte al men (for thine electes ſake in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte) continueſt yet ſo ſtill vntill this day: O traine vs vp alſo in thine heauenly knowledge we pray thée: prepare our harts, teach vs thy law, and wryte thy woordes of life in the tables of oure heartes: that in theſe our monſtrous dayes of moſte wilfull vanitie,<note place="margin">An apt Prayer for theſe oure dayes.</note> which in their ſtrangeneſſe crieth oute (by plagues) to be puniſhed, we may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehande be warned, we may be yet better ſchooled, thy wrath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by preuented, our ſoules more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually nouriſhed, filled with thy fauoure, more mortified daily from the vanities of this brickel life, gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to more thriſtian modeſtie and
<pb facs="tcp:20797:35"/>tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, affected ſolie to the way of holineſſe, comforted in all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and aduerſities, boldned man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully againſt the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies, ſtayed, well armed and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt all temptations, ſtirred vp to the encreaſe of all vertues: that thy woordes (which ſhal iudge vs in the laſt day) being by thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters truely preached, and of vs alſo as zealouſly embraced, and by any meanes not to be deſpiſed or ſlandered, but on all partes ſurely holden, and to ſhewe for the accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly the true frutes of rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, we may be called of thée, thy holy diſciples, &amp; auoide I ſay the ſal of thy ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment alſo to eternal condemnation &amp; be receiued in time to euerlaſting ſaluation: throughe thy grace &amp; the only merites of thy ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20797:35"/>
               <head>IIII. For Fayth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y reading or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy holy worde (O bleſſed ſauiour) we are taught, that true fayth which is thine onely gifte, is onely therby attayned: and that by the power of thine heauenly ſpirite it is breathed into the onely hearts of all thine electe, who receiue it by meaſure and quantitie according to the will and power of the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite: and with thine eyes beholding it in them, thou glorieſt in them, thou daily bleſſeſt them, thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeſt it in them, thy countenance ſhineth vppon them, thou amiably appeareſt and ſhe weſt thy ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: yea ſo acceptable it is in
<pb facs="tcp:20797:36"/>thy ſighte (O ſwéete ſauiour) that thou béeing the king of eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and maieſtie,<note place="margin">Faithe only breathed into the hartes of Gods elect.</note> art eſpouſed to the ſoules of the faithfull, and makeſt them thereby to be partakers with thée of thine heauenly and diuine nature, through the wonderful ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thine holy ſpirite. We are taught by thine holy Apoſtle, that what ſo euer is not of this faith, is ſinne, and that there is no poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without it to pleaſe thée, or to finde grace by ſute at thyne holy hande. And therefore all they that come vnto thée,<note place="margin">True faithe in Chriſte.</note> muſt in déede firmly beléeue, that thou art very God and very Man: yea, and ſuche a God of mighte, of mildeneſſe &amp; great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy aboue all Gods, as both can and euer will heare, incline thine eare, and abundantly rewarde all them, that with liuely and true faith ſéeke thée, and vnfaignedly deſire to finde
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20797:36"/>thée, or to be relieued by thine holy hande. By this fayth (O Lorde) we alſo obteine of God thy father, all good things: yea, what ſo euer we craue at his hande in thy name.<note place="margin">Faithe iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</note> Through this fayth alſo, ſo many as beléeue are iuſtified, made the ſonnes and heires of God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy moſt certainly thereby the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of euerlaſting life. O Lorde Ieſu, great is the power and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this fayth,<note place="margin">The power of Faith.</note> for by it the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the godly are quieted, by it they truely know thée the onely high and eternall God: by it they loue and feare thée, be conſtant to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thée, ſtrong and pacient in al aduerſitie, their hope is firme for things to come: by it they conceiue boldeneſſe to repaire to the throne of thy grace for mercy, to haue ſure truſt in thee, to inuocate thine holy name, to adore and worſhippe it, to
<pb facs="tcp:20797:37"/>confeſſe the truthe before thée, to obey it moſte gladly, to perſeuer therein moſte willingly, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the force of all tyrannie, to yéelde vp in time their ſpirite, and to goe through fayth to thine and their heauenly father. Séeing then (O graciouſe God and Sauiour) that this vertue is ſo heauenly, ſo holy, ſo mightie, ſo acceptable and preciouſe in thy ſight, that without it nothing can be well pleaſing the will of thy maieſtie, or to ſerue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily our owne turnes: and we alſo of ſuche frailtie can not attayne to this moſte ſinguler treaſure, except it come from aboue (euen from thée) and infuſed into our hearts by the grace of thine holy ſpirite: we moſte hartily beſéeche thée (by the power thereof) to make cleane our hearts, to purge them of all error, darkneſſe, and ignorance, of all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20797:37"/>infidelitie, and vnfaythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to plant moſte ſpéedely in vs, a true, liuely, and vndoubted faithe, in the bleſſed and moſte glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinitie: in God our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, in thée (O God) oure only ſauioure, and in the holy ghoſte our moſt deare and ſwéete comfortour: by whome alone, we be all highly bleſſed, preciouſly redéemed, and eternally ſanctified: and that alſo for thine only ſake (O bleſſed ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure) thine heauenly father is well pleaſed with vs, our ſinnes cléerely remitted vnto vs. This faithe (O ſwéete Ieſu) daily encreaſe in vs, help moſt gratiouſly our vnbeléefe, O Lord ſtrengthen vs from faithe to faithe: that we may at the laſte thorow thine accuſtomed grace, be made perfectly faithfull, conſtante warriors, and valiant conquerors, in the defence of thine holy religio,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:38"/>againſte the power of Sathan, the worlde, and Antichriſte: and in all things to ſhe we oure ſelues in this life, bothe in our profeſſion &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, truly and frutefully faithful, euen to the high exaltation &amp; praiſe of thy name: which liueſt and raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, with God the father, and God the holy Ghoſte, true and perfecte God, our onely mediator and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V. To the attainement of Grace, and for the due examination of ſuche deſires and motions, as are put daily into oure mindes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholding (O God our maker) the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in this lyfe, how diuerſly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and in finitely he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20797:38"/>is continually beſet,<note place="margin">The miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate of man in thys life.</note> compaſſed and hedged in with bodily and ghoſtly euil, ſtepping euery moment amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the low ſhrubbes, lurking ſtubbes, ſtumbling blockes, craggie rockes, dead pits, trappes, catches, ſnares, grinnes, furious and fierſe beaſtes, in the wilderneſſe of this worlde to preſent deſtruction: alwayes vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and feareful through danger, whereunto (in his wayes) he may leane or truſt, wandring in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert among doutful chaunces, voide of certain hope, farre off from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, forſaken of frendes, beſet with many enemies, and entiſed diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſundry deſires and motions, &amp; ſo moſte gréenouſly perplexed, and inwardly afflicted in minde, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing before thée (O Lorde) in thine heauenly preſence, vpon hys moſte wretched ſtate, what ſhall betide him, knoweth not what to doe,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:39"/>which way to turne him, whether to flée, not certaine of his ende, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, when, howe, and where he ſhall ende his dayes, and leaue to earthe his moſte wretched and earthie carcaſſe:<note place="margin">Man poſſeſ ſeth in himſelf two powers, and of ſundly inclinations.</note> who during his ſhorte time, poſſeſſeth two powers, diuerſly drawing and leading him: althoughe onely one preuayleth, either with him or againſte him, which is, a willyng conſente to vayne pleaſures bredde in the corrupted fleſhe: or otherwiſe, a more apte inclination to the good wil and motion of the ſpirit, which are bothe contrary the one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the one continually war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or waging battaile againſt the other: whoſe fight (if there be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) are bothe very violente to preuaile, &amp; ſtirreth daily the ſoule to great vnreſt. Which powers or partes of man (O Lord) in the time
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20797:39"/>of innocencie, before the fall of my firſt parents, haddeſt coupled them togither in moſte bleſſed concorde and vnitte, but (alaſſe) nowe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, peace broken and ſet at diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, by the Serpente the enemie of peace and of mankinde:<note place="margin">The ſerpent cauſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde.</note> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue ioyned togither, wythoute contynuall warre, ruffeling and wrangling together as things dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, althoughe in déede but one: I beſéeche thée therefore (O my God the greate God and maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earthe) to beholde with greate compaſſion, my miſerable ſtate among the reſt in this moſte wofull and gréeuous conflicte, my greate frailetie and weakeneſſe wythoute thy grace, my darkneſſe and ignoraunce, and the power of ſinne raygning in myne earthely and mortall members: that as thou arte God the author of peace,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:40"/>the true light and guid, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God of my ſtrengthe, to preuaile for me by thine holy ſpirit, againſt the Prince of ſedition and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of fraud and deceit,<note place="margin">Prince of ſedition.</note> of erroure and lies, and the corrupted motions of the ſinneful fleſhe: ſo graunt me the ſtrengthe of thy grace, a liuely and quicke féeling faithe alſo in thy promiſſes thorowe Chriſte: that thereby my ſpirite being alwayes prepared, quickned and directed by thy ſpirite, it may yéelde to the only quickening and good motions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: that by the heauenly power of it, I may at all times be conſtante in them, and learn perfectly by due examination,<note place="margin">The meane to knowe the good motions from the bad.</note> and with good deſires out of thy worde of truth, the euent of all attemptes, ſtirres, motions, aſſaultes, entiſements, deſſres, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations and affections, to iudge truely of them, to way rightly their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20797:40"/>natures, from whence they come, by what ſpirite, to what ende, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy thy well liking, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to thy glory, anſwerable to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, making for the peace of my conſcience or to the contrary: and ſo by due triall to forſake the one and embrace the other:<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of care leſneſſe, or not to receiue in time the good motions of God.</note> leaſt throughe leude careleſſeneſſe, or not aptly yelding to the good motions of thine holy wil, I giue thine offered grace moſte gracele ſly the ſlippe: becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in thy ſighte but a fugitiue, a reage, a runneagate, a corner crée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, a vaine dullarde, groſe, earthie, lumpiſhe and heauie, voide of ſpirit and life, darke in true iudgemente, affected to vaine deſires, moſte wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly falling from thée, forſaken al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of thee, giuen ouer to my ſelfe, wretchedly wandring at will or at the wilde aduenture, and ſtande as a dead pray to the will of al deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:20797:41"/>aduerſaries: euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſleights of the moſte curſſed ſerpente, to the ſugred baits of this deceitful world, and to the filthie deſires of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious fleſhe: by whome I ſhal be moſt wickedly ſeduced, moſte hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly blinded and fowly corrupted: and ſo trained on in a ſhort race to the ſlaughter, euen to the ſwalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gulffe of deſpaire, the bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hurlepwle, or moſt déepe ſinke of deſtruction. O my god of al mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace,<note place="margin">The power of the ſpirite of light and truthe.</note> that art the only hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of me in all my neceſſities, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and comfort my ſoule with thy ſpirite of lighte and truthe: that I may nowe and at all times bothe truely diſcerne, retaine wyth good will, and folow, the only good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof, and forcibly withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the contrary: that no prouocations, venemous enticementes, or poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pleaſures of the fleſhe, be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20797:41"/>to defile and hazard my ſoule. But folowing the good deſires of the ſpirite (which are moſte pure, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and godly,) and my ſoule euer mindefull of hir celeſtiall nature, enforſing hir ſelfe vpwarde to the high heauens before thy preſence: there may ſpring vp vnto me (all the dayes of my life) the good conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of thy grace, the bleſſed tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie of an innocent minde, the reaped frutes alſo of a good ſpirite, and laſtly in time euerlaſting life, which thou haſt prepared for me thorow thine only mercy and grace, in the merites of thy ſonne and my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior Ieſue Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20797:42"/>
               <head>VI. For the chaſtiſing of the Soule, to keepe it lowe and in ſubiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E be taught of thée (O thou <hi>GOD</hi> of heauen) that who ſo euer wil rightly proſper in this life,<note place="margin">The way and mene to pleſe God in this life.</note> and goe daily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes in true godlyneſſe woorthy thy wel liking, muſt taſt ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of thine heauenly wiſedeme, and enter the way thereto with all lowly ſubiection, holding ſtill faſte thy reuerent feare, eſtéeming vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly the way of thy teſtimonies, and be alwayes very watchful, that he offend not thy ſight. It behooueth vs therfore (O Lord) in the ſtate of our great weakeneſſe and frailetie, and in our darkneſſe and deadly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20797:42"/>to haue daily acceſſe to thée (thou God of our power, true light and wiſedome) by prayer and moſt humble ſute, that we may ſéeke by thine heauenly wiſedome to know thée truly, and to haue thy feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes: that in our profeſſion we may be euer conſtante, pacient and ſtrong in thée, auoiding thorow thy grace al careleſſe ſecuritie, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring inconſtancie and ſlipperneſſe: kéeping all our powers vnder thine holy diſcipline,<note place="margin">Holy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> without repining or murmuring, and not yéelde vp our ſelues (according to the will of the fleſhe) to flying vanities, and the ſwifte flitting things of this world: but cleaue ſtedfaſtly vnto thée, and giue ouer our ſelues wholely, paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to abide thy holy will, to the quickning of vs in our dulneſſe and humaine fearefulneſſe, and to the ſwéete chaſtening of our vntoward
<pb facs="tcp:20797:43"/>and drouſie ſoules. Doubtleſſe (O Lord) very great, ſwéete &amp; pleaſant to the godly, is the commoditie of thy chaſtiſements, and the exerciſes of thy croſſe,<note place="margin">Exerciſes of the croſſe.</note> to the encreaſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe among thy children, and to ſuppreſſe the wil of the proud fleſh: which, otherwiſe to the contrarie, would be ſoone ouerwhelmed with too much pride, iolitie, forgetfulnes, flouth and careleſſeneſſe. Quicken vs therfore (O Lord) with the rod of thy fauoure, viſite at times oure graceleſſe dulneſſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may féele thereby the touche of thy grace, the ſorowes alſo of our mindes in oure offences, and cal our own wayes to remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that we may ſay with the holy Prophet: It is good for me Lord that I haue ben puniſhed, and that to this happie ende, that I may learne thy ſtatutes. Againe, before I was troubled, I went wrong. &amp;c.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20797:43"/>O grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs moſt louing God, that with thy rod of fatherly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we may iudge our ſelues hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, &amp; reioyce with thy holy prophet leaſt to the contrary,<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieuce that commeth by ſufferance and cuill cuſtome.</note> by ſufferance &amp; euil cuſtome, or hauing our reane of wantonneſſe too much at liberty, we too too much deceiue our ſelues, &amp; in our forgetfulneſſe, laughe at our own wickedneſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather moſt bitterly we ſhould bewaile our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber therby the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite dangers to the ſoule, howe it is compaſſed, ſuttlely deceiued, holden captiue &amp; thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l to the diuel. And we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe vnto thée (O our god) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtand not at any time in true li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie or ioy effectual in any thing, onleſſe we poſſeſſe by thy ſpirite thy reuerent feare, &amp; that alſo ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a peaceable &amp; quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. O what a happines therfore is it to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to caſt fréely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, al impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:20797:44"/>lettes of worldly vanities, &amp; yéelde him ſelf wholely vnder thine hand of diſcipline,<note place="margin">He is happie, that humbleth him ſelfe to diſcipline.</note> and to the chaſtening of his ſoule. Graunt vs (O Lord) to be ſo happie, that we may daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and put from vs, what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer may ſtaine &amp; burthen our moſt tender, weake, and ſimple conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Graunt vnto vs in this worlde of warfare, ſtrengthe of thy grace, that we may fighte the battaile of chriſtian ſouldiours, and ouercome by cuſtome, the vſuall ſupporter of all euil. Graunt vs grace (O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lorde) that we may ſtand ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to our charge, yéelde with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience to thy will, and in all things to take ſtraight view of our ſelues, and chéefely with our owne eyes to beholde well our ſelues, that in thy ſight we be all well armed, and ſo alwayes preuent the warning of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the ouerthrow of the dedly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20797:44"/>aduerſarie. Graunt this (o heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) with humbleneſſe of hart we beſéeche thée, to the quick ening and ſtrengthening of oure ſoules in al temptations and chaſtiſements: and ſtirre vp daily in them, thyne heauenly ſparkes and ſwéete moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of comfort, to their moſte hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie reioyſing, and to the exaltation of thy moſte glorious name in this life, and in the euerlaſting world to come: through thy ſon Chriſt our Lorde. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII. For pacience in aduerſitie, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that this worlde is but a place of perigrioation, or paſsing forwardes vnto an other worlde.</head>
               <p>WHen thou in mercie (O lord) beholdeſt thine own, &amp; féeſt them among others
<pb facs="tcp:20797:45"/>how hazardly vnto deadly dangers they daily offer them ſelues, raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging abrode at aduenture like loſte ſhéepe,<note place="margin">Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in preſent danger. God at hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer.</note> and readie to be torn of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſauage and deuouring beaſt: thou by and by of thy fatherly and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der pitie, conſidereſt their miſerable ſtate and condition, and how néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is for them to be ſoughte oute with diligence, to be brought home againe to the folde, or to be pinned in,<note place="margin">Pynches to the proude flesh are ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> fauourably pinched a while in ſome bare paſture, and ſometime to be kept lowe with thy milde touch of calamities and aduerſities, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate their courages, and to let their liuely leapes and oute girdes: by meanes whereof, they be oft called againe, better to remember them ſelues, and whereby they may alſo haue thée the more in minde, and truely to knowe their owne ſtate in this life, whereunto they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20797:45"/>and to whoſe ſeruice, to walke in the wayes of thy preceptes, to kéepe them euer within their bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds and that during their ſhorte race, they liue héere but as exiles or as Pilgrimes farre from theyr owne home, not to liue héere in felicitie,<note place="margin">Man for a time is but an exile from his home, and a pilgrime.</note> not to regarde the pleaſures of thys worlde, either yet to put theyr hope and affiance in them, but to vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without abuſe (as by the way) &amp; but for their only neceſſities homward: we moſte humbly beſeeche thée (O thou father of all mercie) that thou wilt daily renue thy compaſſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, that thou wilt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der vs in our frailty, luſtineſſe &amp; vain iolitie, that in our offences thou wilt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mercie reforme vs, &amp; not vtterly by thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice confound vs: but ſeeke mildely for vs, call vs gently home to thy ſheepfold, with mercie embrace vs, &amp; keepe vs togither for euer in one,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:46"/>in the ſwéete vnitie, felowſhip and amitie of thy flocke. And if at any time, we ſhall hencefoorthe wander abrode and goe aſtray, wherby we ſhall offond thée, and iuſtly incurre thy moſt heauie wrath and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: we craue yet at thine holy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to remember thy mercie, and ſo (in the time of correction) to temper it with thy iuſtice: that we thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by adoption and grace, may largely taſt in that reſpect, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes of thy moſte tender and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly goodneſſe: that as we ſhal for oure diſobedience and ſinne,<note place="margin">The Iuſtice of God and ſinne are not clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeuered in this life amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the children of God.</note> iuſtly feele ſome parte of thy iuſtice, and haue therfore great cauſe of inward gréefe and heauineſſe, &amp; occaſioned daily to grone in our hartes for our ſpéedie deliuerance from thy rodde of correction, and to attaine againe the bright countinunce of thy fauor: ſo we may alſo in the meane time,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20797:46"/>poſſeſſe a liuely faith, ſhewe foorthe the fruites of the ſame, pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually vnto thée, and beare pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy holy will wyth all thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all the dayes of oure lyues: through the only grace of the highe paſtor and chéefe ſhepheard of oure ſoules, thy ſonne our Lord and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>VIII. To be humble in the ſighte of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> My lord God, which arte mine only good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a God of great Maieſtie, and to be bleſſed for euer: I moſte poore and wretched ſinner,<note place="margin">Man but a worme, duſte, and aſhes.</note> moſte vile woorme, duſt and aſhes: and of all others moſte vnwoorthy thy grace and fauour: yet beholding thy great mercie, thy truthe and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:47"/>thy vſual and approued cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, towardes all humble and penitent ſinners: I among the reſt, (but a lumpe of earthe, and ſhaken by thy power to duſt in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:) doe proſtrate my ſelfe vppon the earthe, bewailing before thée my moſte ſinnefull ſtate, crying with the Prophet, <hi>peccaui, peceaui,</hi> and with repentante teares call for thy mercie.</p>
               <p>O my GOD almightie and my maker, which truely knoweſt me thy creature euen as I am, and ſearcheſt thorowly in me, the very ſecretes of the heart and raines: If I ſhould in thy ſight (being nothing of my ſelf) eſteeme any thing of my ſelf or elſe glory in any thing beſids thée vnder the ſunne, thou woldeſt as thou mighteſt by due iuſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte me, woorthily reproue me and condempne me with the reſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20797:47"/>as moſt vaine and for naught. Yea,<note place="margin">Man moſte vayne and naught.</note> mine own ſinnes would accuſe me vnto thée, and my conſcience very terribly crie oute againſt me: for I am before thée but a thing of nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght, and my ſinnes haſt thou ſealed vp againſt me, to the terrifying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of me, and to incurre daily in my mind diuers incommodities &amp; inward anguiſhes, to myne owne ouerthrow and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion. But hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling my ſelfe before thée (O my God) and eſtéeming of my ſelfe, as (in déede I am) but vile duſte and aſhes, and caſt vtterly from me all eſtimation of my ſelfe, being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe (as it were) to nothing: then I truſt I ſhall obtain thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, then ſhall I hope to poſſeſſe the happie peace,<note place="margin">Mans humble ſubiection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth the grace mercy and peace of God.</note> then ſhall I féele true ioy in my ſelf: for thy preſence ſhall be euen at hand, thy grace ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me, thy good ſpirit ſhal quicken
<pb facs="tcp:20797:48"/>me, thy fauorable countinance ſhal cheare me vp, and thine heauenly lighte approche neare mine heart: wherby it ſhall moſt bleſſedly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that where I haue héeretofore moſt vainly eſtéemed, but the leaſt thing of my ſelfe, the ſame very vaine or ſmall eſtimation concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſhall ſodenly conſume and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe to naught for euer: and ſhall thencefoorth by the hand of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, be ſo vndor propped and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly holden vp, that I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer decline from due conſideration of my ſelfe, what I am of my ſelfe, what I haue bene, by whom I haue my being, and from whence I am come: namely, of nothing, and from nothing: and being ſo lefte vnto my ſelfe, I ſhall be founde nothing, but only as a ſhadow, or méere infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and weakeneſſe.<note place="margin">Man a thing of nothing.</note> Therefore, I moſt humbly beſéeche thée (O thou
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20797:48"/>father of al mercy) the only aſſured ſtay of thine inheritance, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely chaſeſt away the vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of man, turne a little towardes me, tender me in my weakeneſſe, and ſhewe me the ſtrengthe of thy countenaunce, that immediatly in thée I may be ſtrong, and newely chéered vp with inwarde and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly gladneſſe: that being entred into moſt ſodaine admiration with my ſelfe, to ſée my ſelf in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by thy fatherly embracement, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp to heauen; which by myne owne proneneſſe and waighte of ſinne, was before caryed downe to hell, I may thanke thée my moſte ſwéete and louing God, and prayſe thée with an humble and moſte lowly heart, with continual mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, zealouſly, religiouſly and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in thought, woord and déede: tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thy mercie and grace in thy
<pb facs="tcp:20797:49"/>ſonne Ieſus Chriſte all the dayes of my life. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX. Of true obedience and ſubiection, to ſuche as be in authoritie, according to the woorde of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father) as it is rather auaileable for men in this worlde, to be in ſubiection to other,<note place="margin">It is better for a man to obey, than to leane to his owne ſway.</note> than to leane to their owne only ſway and leude li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: and ſo, muche more ſafely to obey, than to beare rule, and haue all at commaundemente: with all humbleneſſe we beſéeche thée, to directe vs with thy ſpirite of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and lowelineſſe, and to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in ſubiection to aucthoritie,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20797:49"/>according to thy woorde by the rule of thine holy Apoſtle: not onely for feare, for neceſſitie, and therefore painefully: but rather of true loue, duetifully, moſte gladly, and that for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>For otherwiſe (O Lorde) wée ſlippe from our Chriſtian profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, true obedience, and moſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerente ſubiection, and attaind not the true libertis of minde, and the ſhewing of obedyence from the hearte, and for Goddes ſake:<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that commeth by diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> but fall of will moſte wickedly, and as bonde ſlaues, into the ſinne of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, contempte, murmuring, grut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, conſpiring, rebelling, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to innumerable ſuche like, as men being wholely giuen ouer to a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked will, runnyng headlong into all kinde of miſcheefes: whereby we become as reſectes, and caſte awayes from thy glorious fauoure:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:50"/>we purchaſe thy diſpleaſure, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our treacheries, the curſſe of the people ſhall fall vpon vs, the ſpoile of the innocentes, and theyr bloud ſhed ſhall crie for vengeance againſt vs, our dayes ſhalbe ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, our offſpring and family aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; vtterly confounded, contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and for euer brought to naught. O gratious God, graunt therefore that we may euer regarde thy wil, be mindefull of thy ſtatutes, feare thy indgements, and conſider with our ſelues, oure chriſtian obedience and duetie towardes aucthoritie, walking humbly in oure vocation before thée, to the vpholdyng of peace, to the contenting of aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to render vnto them their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to the benefiting of oure Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to the bleſſing of our poſteritie, and to remember alſo with this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured perſuaſion, that whether ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20797:50"/>euer we turne oure ſelues in thus life, we ſhall not aptly finde reſt in any place, if we be ſeditious, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chéeuouſly inclined, traiterous, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators or rebellyous:<note place="margin">The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God ouer ſeditious rebelles.</note> for thy iudgements will ſtill folow vs, thy ſwoorde ſhall deuoure vs, and cruel meſſengers ſhall be ſente againſte vs, as of many we haue both herd, read, and oft times knowne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs. For thou (O Lord) in the feruor of thy zeale, neither canſt nor wilte ſuffer the higher powers, ſo to be diſobeyed or vnnaturally ſpurned againſt: but thou wilt by thy iuſtice ſée it ſharpely reuenged, as the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence verily committed, againſt the perſone of thine eternall maieſtie. Giue vs grace therfore (O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) we humbly beſéeche thée, to way reuerently thy will in thy woord, and accordingly to liue in all ſubiection to the higher powers, to
<pb facs="tcp:20797:51"/>pray daily &amp; moſt hartily for them,<note place="margin">Princes and Magiſtrates are the moſt apte Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſtirred of God, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his glory here vppon earth.</note> as for the apte inſtrumentes of thy grate, and furtherers of thy glory, at theſe dayes of true lighte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt touche daily &amp; deepely all their harts, with the finger of thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly grace, that thy principall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite may for euer poſſeſſe them, and that thy bleſſings alſo may daily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde bothe vpon them, vpon vs, and vpon oure poſteritie (as vpon the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of true obedience, peace and humbleneſſe) to our reioying and praiſing of thy glorious name, vntill the ende of this life and for euer: thorowe Ieſus Chriſte oure one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lorde and Sauioure. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20797:51"/>
               <head>X. For the Queenes moſte excellenre Maieſtie, for hir Honourable Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures, hir whole Court or familie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie God and father of all mercie, which gratiouſly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneſt, moſte wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruleſt, and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly bleſſeſt héere vppon earthe, thy great Congregation, the pillar and grounde of truthe, the flocks of Chriſte, thine holy Churche, the Spouſe of Chriſte, the elect veſſels of thy mercie, thine whole houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and familie: whoſe God of mercie thou only art throughoute all generations, and helper in all oure néedes and neceſſities: and haſte appointed therein by thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ordinaunce, temporall rulers,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:52"/>Princes and Magiſtrates, to rule and gouerne thy people, according to equity and the rule of rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for the aduauncement of the good, and pumſhmente of the euill: and haſt alſo al their harts in thine holy hand, to direct, ſanctiſte, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne them after thine owne will to the godly example of others, and to ſet foorthe (amongſte them) thy glory: haue mercy vpon thy ſeruant Elizabeth, our noble and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Quéene, in the excellencie of hir moſt high calling, holy ſeruice, and of greate charge before thée in thy ſanctified Churche: that as hir heart (ſpecially) being truely dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in thy ſight by the ſpirit of light and truthe, to the true knowledge, perfect obedience, and ready furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy will, with all chriſtian diligence and ſeruencie, (as aboue all things beſt behooueth hir moſte
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20797:52"/>gratious and royall maieſtie: that the rather in all other hir neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhée may at all times be moſte aſſuredly bleſſed by thée, releeued, comforted, ſtrengthened, mightely defended and deliuered bothe in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule:) ſo alſo, the honorable hir beloued, graue, and prudente Counſellors, faithful miniſters vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hir &amp; whole familie, may euery of them in their degrée, chriſtian vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or faithfull ſeruice, duetifully waie with them ſelues, the vertue of their charge, ſtraight bande and profeſſion before thée, ſéeking truely vnder hir highneſſe (for thy glorye and hir honoure) the fruteful know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy lawes: that in theyr ſtate of great excellency, right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful calling, meane ſtate, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioure miniſterie, (whether of the Cleargie, as they are termed, or of the laitie) they may haue the feare
<pb facs="tcp:20797:53"/>and true obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce before their eyes, framing vnfainedly all their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, their actions and dueties, by the only rule of thy woorde of life:<note place="margin">What it is to imitate chriſt.</note> walking vprightly therein, holily, and religiouſly, in thought, woorde, and déede, with vndeſiled, pure and peaceable conſciences, to the daily edifying, encouraging and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of all others: that thereby hir whole Court or Princely fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being through fulneſſe of vertue and thine heauenly wiſedome wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull to beholde, woorthily noted of all, delighted in of all, and moſte highly commended of al, may be of all moſte dearely beloued, highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéemed, ioyfully receiued, thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſed, practiſed and folowed, as a moſte preciſe patron of all perfect and true pietie: as a very brighte, large, and cleare ſhining light, déep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly piercing, inwardly quickening,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20797:53"/>farre extending and reaching ouer al, or as a cleare ſountaine or quick ſpringing water; deſcending from an high, moſt beautifull to looke on, moſt pleaſant to taſte on, very dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, moſt neceſſary, helthfull and comfortable, common to all, ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly running towardes all, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced of all, and into al partes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to hir highneſſe or round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout hir: wherby, through the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, healthfulneſſe, clearneſſe, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; fulneſſe therof, al hir people (and others) drawing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and taſting abundantly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, may long be preſerued, healthfully noriſhed, vpholde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vortue, in true religion &amp; honeſtie, all the dayes of their liues, that in ſtead of thy terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and wrathfull indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations due vnto all, for diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, contempt and ſinfulneſſe, thy moſte gracious &amp; fatherly bleſſings
<pb facs="tcp:20797:54"/>(as ſwéete dews from heauen) may alwayes moſt comfortably, fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably with ſpéede and abundantly, light both vpon hir highneſſe, vpon hir Nobilities whole Courte and whole Countrey, to thine only ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, praiſe and glory, euen in the ſight and faces of all hir and our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: that they may plainely ſée it, may be aſhamed of their errour, of their darkneſſe, wilful madneſſe, great diſobedience, wicked atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes and contemptes, and may be more mindefull of thée, thou greate God of rightuouſneſſe, ſéeke moſt gladly in truthe to knowe thée, to feare thine holy name, to be conuerted vnto thée, and to bleſſe wyth vs in rightuouſneſſe al the dayes of their liues, thorow thy ſon Ieſus Chriſt, and for his ſake, our only ſauioure, our only mediatoure and aduocate. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20797:54"/>
               <head>XI. Againſt vaine hope and pride.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde, that art only omnipotente,<note place="margin">How we ſhold for the greate loue of God, lone hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</note> milde and mercyfull, and the only perfect hope of thy beloued inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance: vpon whom thy grace hath moſte fréely aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and whoſe ſinnes thou haſte remitted, by the onely oblation, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and bloude ſhed of thy deare ſorme Chriſt Ieſus: for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe and moſte pretious redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou only requireſt of them, but to be beloued againe: and that with an vpright ſtaysdneſſe, an aſſured ſtrength and true confidence only in thée: and not otherwiſe vainely, in any vaine man, or other trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and that they be not hautie
<pb facs="tcp:20797:55"/>in theyr owne eyes, but poſſeſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in thy ſighte &amp; in them ſelues, the ſpirit of méekeneſſe, and of moſt lowly ſubmiſſion: we moſt entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſéeche thée, to ſtrengthen vs héerein with thine: heauenly grace, to ſtay vs vnto thy ſelfe, &amp; to make vs humble in oure owne eyes: that imitating the ſteppes of thy ſonne, we be not aſhamed to beare in thy ſight, the contempt of this wretched world, and to become with all low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and milde ſubiection, euen very ſlaues to all others, for the loues ſake of thy deare ſonne Ieſus: whoſe rule of Humilitie we haue moſte truely profeſſed, and thereby promiſſed to beare with pacience, bothe pouertie and all other affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in thys vale of wretched; neſſe, where, when, and in what manner ſo euer it ſhall pleaſe thée to lay them vppon vs.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20797:55"/>
               <p>O Lord, ſo vpholde thou vs with thine heauenly grace, that we ſtaie not ſimplie vpon our owne ſelues, or putte oure truſte in others: but flee faſte from our ſelues and from all others, and put oure whole and onely hope in thée: endeuouring with all our powers (bothe of bodie and minde) to obey thy will, &amp; truſt only in thée, that thou wilt always be the readie helper of oure good willes, and a moſte apte furtherer of all oure honeſt meanings. Lette thy mercie (O Lorde) ſo be vppon vs, that we be not vainely puffed vppe, or putte confidence eyther in oure owne knoweledge, or in the pollicie of any mortall manne: but onely depende vppon thy Diuine &amp; fatherly prouidence, which both helpeſt and géeueſt thy grace to the humble, and thruſteſt alſo downe the loſtie and proude.
<pb facs="tcp:20797:56"/>So temper vs lord with thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly grace, that we glory neither in our richeſſe if we haue them, nor yet in our fréendes if they be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (for thou moſte mightie God haſte dominion ouer their power, and when thèy are alofte, and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their glorie, thou throweſt them downe, abateſt their corage, and deſtroyeſt them with thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d:) but to glory (as we ought) only in thée, which doeſt fréely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto vs all things neceſſarie, and deſtreſt aboue all, to giue thine owne ſelfe wholely vnto vs. Thou (O Lorde) haſte led vs the way to true humilitie: that whether tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching either the mightineſſe,<note place="margin">Humilitie.</note> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or cômlineſſe of the body (which being ſtricken with ſome light diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, is by and by ouerthrowne and defaced) we in no wiſe aduaunce our ſelues. And leaſt we ſtand moſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20797:56"/>vainely in our owne conceits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for oure owne towardeneſſe, wiſedome, wit, or in other things, iudge better of our owne ſelues tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we doe of others, we greatly offend and fall into thine heauie diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and bring thy wrathe vppon vs: bicauſe we eſtéeme them not as thine owne proper giftes, and ſo be thankefull vnto thée for them. O graunt vnto vs therfore (moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious God) thy ſpirite of méekeneſſe and true humbleneſſe, that we may walke rightly before thée, and haue in our ſelues and in thy ſight, cleane hartes, conſtantelaithe, and moſte ſure hope and conſidence: trauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually thy ſpirit of romfort, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently therby to beare our croſſe, to folowe the example of our ſauioure Chriſt, and to beare with ioy the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of this life through his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, precious death &amp; paſtion. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20797:57"/>
               <head>XII. Againſt Couetouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we (O thou iuſt &amp; terrible God) coulde nowe thorowe thy grace, euen in the middeſt of all oure iniquities, heaping daily iniquitis vppon iniquitie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member yet in time, thy certaine deter minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and threaiued iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon this world,<note place="margin">God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the world for ſinne.</note> &amp; the plages thereof ſhortly enſtring for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> harte: and as thou haſte tolde: vs by thy Prophet Eſay, to lay to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to make the face of the whole earth deſolate, and ſcatter abrode all the inhabitoures thereof, bicauſe they haue offended thy lawes, changed thine ordinali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; and made thine euer laſting te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: receiuing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20797:57"/>therfore with wee, their moſt ſharp &amp; bitter portion, the taſte of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fury, vtter ſhame, deſolation &amp; ſwift confuſion: O what cauſe haue we then to remember in theſe oure dayes (if through grace it might be for good) this moſt vile ſin abidng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, the outragious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">The Canker couetouſneſſe how it reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</note> that ſo diuerſty woorketh the diſglory of thy name, &amp; ſpoyleth thy churches welfare? Which, in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation of this worlde ſo langely raigneth, ſo vniuerſally; ſo famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly, yea, &amp; alſo mercileſly: ouerflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth al, deuoureth al, hath al at his beck, and haſtneth faſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iteration (an euil and pitileſſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doubtleſſe, in the end now of this olde rotten worlde) the ſodaine and ſtraight performance of thy hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous and fearefull premiſſes. O Lord our God, moſte dangerous is our ſtats, our dayes are moſt euill,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:58"/>our deſertes are great, we haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned greuouſly, thy plagues are iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared, and thy iudgements to condemnation, by thy iuſtice are at hand vpon vs. For who in effecte ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay (from any ſin) his hart is clean? or rather moſt mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruouſly againſt nature, not to be defiled? either who can in conſcience ſay, that he féeles not in him ſelfe (as priuately for him ſelfe and corruptly,) this moſt hurtfull and infectuous maladie of the ſoule? which amongſt, all other contagious euils, is moſte pernice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by the diuel him ſelf déepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grafted in vs, and is by him ſo cloſely crept in vnto vs, that it hath ioyned it ſelfe, euer to the very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete affections of our hartes, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelfe a moſt diligent woorker,<note place="margin">Conetouſnes how it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</note> a buſie labourer or miniſter, to the procuring, bréeding, encreaſing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and bringing forthe of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20797:58"/>ruption and ſinnes innumerable, couertly lurking in our filthie fleſh, &amp; ſowly to the death, iſſueth abrode in his time. For it is (as ſayth thine holy Apoſtle) the roote of all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chéefe: and that all ſuche alſo as are the Rauens and gréedie Gripes or gutlings of the world, and deſirous of the deceiteful riches thereof, fall without ſtay into temptations and ſnares, and into many beaſtly, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and noiſome luſts, which draw them into temptation and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.<note place="margin">Couetouſnes, the woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping of Idols.</note> Alſo, he calleth it, a woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of idols: it ſpoileth God of his honor: and is therby in euery place of the holy Scriptures condemned and forbidden, as a ſinne moſt hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, horrible, diuelliſhe and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: bicauſe it is a moſte curſſed and venemous euill, tied to ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hautie and vaineglorious, full of maliciouſneſſe, ful of crueltie, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:20797:59"/>tirannous, and greeoely hunteth after bloud: the déepe ſet ſéede dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of the diuell, who was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer from the beginning, &amp; hathe therewith by his ſubteltie,<note place="margin">Couetouſneſſe he we it hathe preuayled.</note> maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly preuailed vpon the earth, and broughte into ſubiection, not onely the moſt vnfaithfull, very reiectes, and wicked caſte awayes from thy fauour, (who being but earthly, ſet their whole felicitie vppon earthly things) but euen the very profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors alſo of thy moſte holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed religion. For in all eſtates and degrées, from the moſt to the leaſt, from the higheſt to the loweſt, all are defiled therewith, al bend their wittes moſte graceleſly and inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately to vnſatiable couetouſneſſe, excéeding farre the limits of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſcraping &amp; gathering togither, as the children of diffidence &amp; very worldlings,<note place="margin">Children of diffidence.</note> contrary to the lawe of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20797:59"/>nature, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the law of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or chriſten holineſſe and puritie, whether by righte or by wrong, by hooke, by crooke, by extortion, by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, by flattery, by periury, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, vſury, bribery, ſimony, priuy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracy againſt town, citie, prince and the whole countrey: greedie of vengeance, yea, by what meanes ſo euer it be, &amp; oft by moſt wilful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to murther, whether of others, or through indigence, lacke of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie, or by ſome ſiniſter ſtroke of fortune, deſperately deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Such are our willes to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes (o lord) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> being voide of thy grace, we ſink déepely into al abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, &amp; are altogither without moderation or ſtay of our appetites affectionately grubbing for more &amp; more, til death cut vs ſhort, till our mouths be filled with grauel,<note place="margin">Abac. 2.</note> or til we heape vp (as the Prophet ſaith)
<pb facs="tcp:20797:60"/>thick clay againſt our ſelues, feling the iuſtice of the rightuous god, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome we are fled, and haue putte oure only affiaunce, in wicked and vaine filthie Mammon. To the end therfore (O moſte louing God) we may in thée be better ſtaide, oure liues in thy feare more aptly fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and oure faultie faithes more chriſtianly reformed, graunte that by thy woorde we may truly know thée, obey thy wil, put our only truſt in thée, loue thée, as our god of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and reuerence thée as our Lorde of iuſtice. Graunte vnto vs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of thine heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly grace, that our graceleſſe, indurate, and moſte barraine hartes, being thus bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and hardned by the diuel, may he by thée moſte gratiouſly refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, frutefully tempered, déepely indued, thorowly ſoftened, ſowen with thy celeſtiall ſéedes, well har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20797:60"/>rowed and made truely profitablé, that thy holy Church, may thereby be ſpéedely purged of this very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and moſte peſtilent infection, nowe raigning with outrage ouer all the world. Wherof, bicauſe our liues ſtandeth not in the abundance of theſe vanities which we héer poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, thy ſonne Chriſt left ſtraighte charge vnto vs (the profeſſoures of his name) in any wiſe to beware of Couetouſneſſe. Roote out therefore we pray thée (O God) from oure hartes, oure vnſatiable and gréedie deſires. O incline oure hartes vnto thy teſtimonies, and not to coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſeneſſe: but yéelding to thy will with contented mindes in oure cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, we may in all our neceſſities, caſt gladly our cares vpon thy back that art truly rich, almightie, a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die helper, very mindeful and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful vnto vs, for oure ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuement,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:61"/>and to further therby thy glory. Prepare vs to be charitable, frée harted and liberall, to haue in vs the bowels of compaſſion, to be pitiful alwayes to the poore, to yéeld to ſufficiencie, too neither riches nor pouertie, to remember we nakedly entred this world, that we ſhall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nothing oute of this world, that we muſte forſake the worlde, for it will forſake vs, away néedes we muſte, we are heere but ſtrangers, our yeares are but few, our calling ſodain, death tarieth not, death ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, death areſteth, our recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning muſte be made, oure iudge is iuſt, our witneſſe is true, oure ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is determined, oure place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, our rewarde prepared, and moſte preciouſly purchaſed (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father) for thine holy electe &amp; obedient children, by the only death and bloud ſhed of thy ſon our deare Lord &amp; ſauior Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:20797:61"/>
               <head>XIII. Againſt Adultrie and Whoredome.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuche (O eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God) as thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arte moſte rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, pure, holy, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and abhorreſt from thine harte, the ſtinking ſin of luſt, adultry, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, fornication &amp; ſuch like: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt alſo of vs in the .vij. precept, that in our liues &amp; conuerſation we be like vnto thée in all puritie &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and in any wiſe not to defile or once ſpot our ſelues, with the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of vnlawful luſtes or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe:<note place="margin">Conſtancie in chaſtitie.</note> but conſtantly hold &amp; kéep faſt, the integritie of oure faithfull promiſſe made vnto thée our onely Lorde God, bothe in the calling of our ſole liues,<note place="margin">Sole life.</note> and in the holy ſtate alſo of matrimonie (which in the ſighte of thée, is very honourable,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:62"/>of highe perfection, and great excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie) and is amongſte men in thy holy Churche,<note place="margin">Matrimonie a fountayne in Gods church.</note> as it were the louely fountaine or wel ſpring of good life, not only in the beautifying of them ſelues thorow their own clereneſſe in chaſtitie, but floweth forthe alſo (by example &amp; doctrine) with moſte ſwéete taſte to their owne beloued offſpring and familie, and to the apt ſeaſoning likewiſe of the ſingle and vnmaryed ſorte: we moſt humblye beſéeche thée to take from vs in our weakeneſſe and frailty, the violent power of fleſhe and bloude, and to quenche in vs continually,<note place="margin">The corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fleshe and bloud.</note> the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging luſtes of oure vncleane &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bodies: which inwardly moueth violently ſtirreth, ſtriueth, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, inflameth, burneth, altereth ſore the body, amaſeth the minde, ſpoileth the ſenſes, maketh menne mad, or turneth the vnwiſe of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20797:62"/>worlde quite beſide their wittes. O God, that art maker of all makind, thou ſéeſt all things, thou beholdeſt al our doings, thou knoweſt the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of our hartes, and howe by nature, we are naturally enclined to ſuche euill, and giuen to féele in our weakeneſſe, the ſmarts of oure infections, boyling &amp; ſoming fumes of the fickle and fraile fleſhe,<note place="margin">The power of fleſh and blud, and what they worke.</note> and ſtirred daily therby to greate abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and filthineſſe, to haſten vpon our ſelues, the heat of thy fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and fierce vengeance, becauſe we haue vowed, as thou haſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, ſuche euils to be eſchued, and none adulterie or the ſyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenneſſe to be commicted: for as thou (O Lordo) haſte called vs, ſo haue we yéelded to thy cal, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed thée, to walke before thée in puritie and holyueſſe of life, being made of many members, one body
<pb facs="tcp:20797:63"/>and one ſpirite with thée: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the harte to abhorre all vnclenneſſe, and not to be defiled &amp; made the members of an harlot: for we know, that no fornicator, filthie adulteror, whoremonger, abuſer of himſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mankinde, no vncleane perſon nor weakeling, ſhal inherite thine heauenly kingdome, O father of all merey and grace, let not the deſues then of ſuche corruption and vurlenlineſſe, faſton their roote of death vppon vs, neither to be giuen ouer to an vnſhamefaſt and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate minde, flying from thy holy will in our profeſſion, contemning the act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>table countels of the godly or alſo neglecte the terrible exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of thy iuſtice a written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">The pumiſhe ments of God for vnclennes of lyſe.</note> and to print with faith in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone, that for ſuche abhomination and wickedneſſe, thou haſte plaged the ear the: The olde worlde was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20797:63"/>drouned, the Sodomites, the reſt of the .v. Cities, and their whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, with firie flames, ſulpher and Brimſtone from heauen were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: with ſuche other like the terror of thy vengeance, by ſharpe plages &amp; puniſhments vpon others, cléerly mentioned in thy holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, plainly approued in other hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and daily both knowne and felt amongſt vs. O moſt gratious &amp; louing father, create therfore in vs we beſéeche thée, hunble, contrite &amp; clean harts, renue within our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els right ſpirites, and turne all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe away from vs, that neither in thought, word, nor déede, we willingly offend the ſight of thy maieſtie. And graunt that whether we liue vnmattried, or in the holy ſtate of Matrimonie, we may leade our liues in puritie, true holineſſe and chaſtitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20797:64"/>
               <p>And when at any time we féele in our ſelues to be aſſalted with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or ſtirred by euil luſte to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit obhomination, we may then haue ſtrengthe of thy grace to ſette before oure eyes, thy iuſtice, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of ſinne, the terror of deathe, the day and end of this life, the gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing worme of our conſcience, thy terrible doome, the chalenge of the Deuill, the euerlaſting tormentes, and the horrible paines of hell. And that we liuing in oure chriſtian cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and holy profeſſion, in all puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hothe of bodie and ſoule all the dayes of our liues, we may receiue in the ende the rewarde of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting felicitie, &amp; ſée thée face to face in thine eternall and moſt glorious kingdome, thorow thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:20797:64"/>
               <head>XIIII. A Prayer againſt ſvvearing and blaſphemie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen we (O holy &amp; eternall God) haue in remembraunce (as we be charged) thy preciſe wil and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, giuen generally vnto vs all, and binding vs all from euil: namely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the reſt, not to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thée our god in vain, nor in any wiſe to abuſe it,<note place="margin">To bee a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer of Gods name, is rather the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertie of an ethnik than a Chriſtian.</note> as doth the wicked Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieke, (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth not thy name) irreligiouſly, vainly and falſoly: but at all times to, conſider well: of it, highly to extoll it, and haue it in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerence, as behooneth the faithful louers and profeſſors of the ſame, leaſt we be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of thee accurſſed
<pb facs="tcp:20797:65"/>and guiltie, and ſuſtaine as thou haſt threatned, thy moſte iuſte and ſharpe reuenge: we are héere great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſioned to conſider our preſent and moſte daungerous ſtate, howe vnperfecte, wretched and dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is in thy ſighte, throughe oure deadly fal from thy will in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly precept, and are nowe driuen cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſéeke remedie at thine onely mercifull hande, or to periſhe in hel eternally: we beſéethe thée moſte humbly (O thou God of all grace) that as thou beholdeſt in vs, the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure of oure liues, and oure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted inclination to all ſinne and vanitie,<note place="margin">The errour of our liues.</note> contrary to the preſcripte rule of thy holy lawe, and to ſéeke thereby (as muche as ut vs lyeth) the diſglory of thy name, &amp; to worke our owne ſhame and vtter confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou: ſo to graunt nowe vnto vs, that oure ſoules in their vnclenlineſſe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20797:65"/>horribleneſſe &amp; blaſphemous ſtate, may be truly purged of al infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">The power of Gods word.</note> deadly darkneſſe, wilfull malice, &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and the ſights of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, quickened, made liuely and perfecte, by the bright light and true faith in thy holy woorde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may cléerely and comfortably ſee, know, and beholde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true glory of thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, &amp; thereby alſo inwardly féele the ſwéete promiſſes of thine heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace, the frée pardone alſo of all our ſinnes, and the receiuing of vs into thy grace &amp; fauor, not for any thing at all in our ſelues, but for thy ſonne Chriſte Ieſus ſake: throughe which only mercy and great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe graunted vnto vs in him, thou arte, and of righte euer oughteſt to be only eſtomed of vs, only praiſed, magnified, and highly reuerenced,<note place="margin">The mercy of God in Chriſt.</note> as thy name (in heauen &amp; in earth) moſte condignely of all requireth:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:66"/>which is from vs, euen ſo muche in euery reſpect, as we in déede truely know thée in thy ſonne Chriſte: by whome only and throughe grace in him, we are ſtirred moſt woorthily to extol thy moſt glorious and holy name: but not ſo lightly by cuſtome to prophane it, and vnreuerently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it: whether by cruell blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, contempte of thine heauenly woorde, true religion &amp; doctrine, or otherwiſe in our ſinneful conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or euill maner of liuing. Take vs therefore we pray thée to thy mercie (O Lord) and that ſoone, for great is our ſinne and iniquitie, in this accuſtomed ſinne of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. O ſet thy feare ſpéedely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, and ſhut not vp from vs the knowledge of thy truthe,<note place="margin">The inconue niece that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the want of Gods worde.</note> our director to rightuouſneſſe: but kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle inwardly into oure ſoules, the lighte thereof: leaſte in the deadly
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20797:66"/>darkeneſſe, pride and great peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of our wicked harts, we do dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly degenerate, turne from our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, fall willingly from thée, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ingratefull, vaine, proude and high minded, contumelious &amp; ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſhameleſſe, open enimies, and very blaſphemous againſte thée, as the only poſſeſſors of the deuill, and falling like reprobates, from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie to iniquitie. Who, for theyr horrible abuſes ſake and prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy name, how they ſhall be woorthily plaged (thine hande of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice not being ſhortned) is plainely euident in thy moſt ſacred and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly woord of truthe. For thou thy ſelfe haſte ſaide: that what ſo euer he be that is a blaſphemer, &amp; vſeth thy name vainly and vnprofitably,<note place="margin">The puniſhe ments and plages of God for taking his name in vaine.</note> ſhall not eſcape thy ſcurges and pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhments. And in an other place it is alſo wrytten: that who ſo euer v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:20797:67"/>muche to ſweare, ſhall be filled with curſſings and iniquity: and the plage, which is the iuſte bengeance of thy wrath, ſhall neuer depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his houſe, but ſhal in time conſume it, and all the inhabitantes thereof. Again, we read out of thy Prophet Zacharie, that thou ſhewedſt vnto him flying in the air, a maruellous large and a great booke, euen .xx. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites in length, &amp; .x. in bredth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was contained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> horrible plages that are prepared for all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which contemptuouſly, malitiouſly, vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, falſly, or raſhely, ſweare by thy bleſſed and holy name. O Lorde of infinite mercies, and long ſuffering God, that art to be bleſſed for euer, whoſe mercyes reacheth vnto the heauens:<note place="margin">The neceſſitie of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> if thou in theſe our dayes of great abhomination, curſſed bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheming, &amp; taking thy holy name in vaine, ſo careleſſy, vſually, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20797:67"/>by cuſtome for euery ſmal trifle, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other deadly and dampnable ſinnes daily committed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, ſhouldeſt in the iudgement of thine owne cauſe, flerſly riſe vp againſte vs, or as thy Prophet Dauid ſayth, extréemely marke what is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, O Lord how ſhuld we abide it? How ſhould we (moſte ſinnefull wretches) in theſe dayes, abide the terror of thy vengeance, that by thy iuſtice hangeth ouer vs, or ſhould in a moment conſume vs all like ſtubble. But thou rewardeſt vs not according to our ſinnes, thy mercie endureth for euer, and therefore to auoide the terror of thy iuſtice, due vnto vs moſt diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſinners, we appeale to the déep fountains of thy mercy,<note place="margin">Sute for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> humbling our ſelues before thy mercies ſeat, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> penitent harts, for the remiſſion of our ſins, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt not impute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now vnto vs,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:68"/>but for the glory of thy name, to mollifie, to cleanſe, and alwayes to kéepe cleane, oure harde, ſtonie and euill ſtuffed hartes, with the déepe piercing deawe of thine heauenly grace: that where all thoſe terrible puniſhmentes and moſte gréeuous plagues before mentioned, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deuiſed, prepared, threatned, and at an inſtant appoynted to fall vpon vs: we may yet by thy mercie eſcape them, extoll thée in thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodneſſe,<note place="margin">The ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods holy name.</note> and magnifie thine holy name, from our hartes, and with our tongs and voices, and feare to prophane or abuſe it: no, neither yet thy creatures in heauen or in earth: but moſt humbly with al ioyfulneſſe to attend to thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes moſt holy precept: which is, not to ſweare at all by any thing, but in our communication to vſe, yea yea, nay nay, euen from hart and mouth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20797:68"/>ſimply, truly, and without diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: and to paſſe forthe our liues and conuerſation in our calling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently, ſincerely, and vncorrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as becommeth faithfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained Chriſtians, the true louers and profeſſoures of thine only holy name, which is to be bleſſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>XV. For the poſſeſſyng of a peaceable and quiet conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing thy kingdome (O GOD) as thou ſayeſt, is within vs, and that it behooueth as thou haſte taught vs, to haue outward things of this world, and the world it ſelfe in contempt, and to embrace only with good affecte, all inwarde
<pb facs="tcp:20797:69"/>things, to the beautifying of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde man, whereby we ſhall the more aptly féele in déede, thine holy kingdome to come into vs: which kingdome is thine, moſt high, moſt glorious,<note place="margin">The kingdom of heauen.</note> holy, eternall and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, a kingdome of ioy and peace in the holy ghoſt: whereof, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hathe no parte in poſſeſſion, but only thine holy electe and precious redéemed inheritaunce. Graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs all we humbly pray thée, ſuch loue towardes thée, and thine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome, that for thy ſake, and for the loue therof, we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenine our ſelues, eſtéeme but light of this life, and ſet all this world at naughte. And being lifted vp in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite aboue oure ſelues, and voide of all inordinate deſires, excelling in oure liues in all heauenly vertues, and be ſuche in déede inwardly, as we ſéeme to the worlde outwardly,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20797:69"/>our ſoules may be made fit habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to enioy thy glorious preſence with moſt happy felicitie, extolling thy grace, glorying in the woorkes of true holyneſſe,<note place="margin">A quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> and in the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of a peaceable and quiette conſcience, which is in all menne a ſecrete knowledge,<note place="margin">The nature of a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> a priuie ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, inwarde accuſer, a ioyfull qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter of their myndes in all their dooings, and a witneſſe bearer of the truthe, euen vnto the preſence and preciſe iudgement of thée oure God.</p>
               <p>O graunt therfore vnto vs (moſt gratious God) ſo to be directed by thy holy ſpirite, that oure conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may be vnto vs vnſtained and pure, euen as a very perfecte and cleare glaſſe, ſpeedely to be looked into, and plainely to ſée in tyme, with a true and perfecte ſighte, not onely the moſte filthy foule ſpottes
<pb facs="tcp:20797:70"/>and enormious blemiſhes of oure ſinnefull and ſicke ſoules, but alſo the very ſmalleſt or beginnings of diſeaſes, by ſoone quicke touche or ſharpe pricke of remorſe, whereby feare may be conceiued of imminet daunger, and by humble ſute to flée faſt vnto thée the moſte readie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte and heauenly Phiſition, that we may be ſoone ſalued wyth the oyntment of thy diuine grace:<note place="margin">Wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</note> and not to be as the wicked, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are moſte déepely corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inwardly rankeled, deade and benummed, throughe careleſneſſe and the cuſtome of ſinne: that they cannot once féele, ſée, nor perceyue, their owne moſt lothſome ſickneſſe and deformitie of ſoule: vntill thou (O God) by the ſtroke of thy dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly darte, layeſt them open before theyr faces, to their own confuſion, ſodaine and ſwifte deſtruction: and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20797:70"/>ſo their conſciences being now fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d moſt déepely wounded, &amp; the worm therof terribly gnawing, biting and accuſing them, they fall moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably into deſperation, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thy maieſtie, or any hope at all of thy tender mercie. O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, and the only fountaine of all grace, tourne thy face from oure ſinnes, deliuer vs from thy wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indignation, and ſo ſtrengthen vs by the power and lighte of thine eternal ſpirit, that we may be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the true knowledge and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte obedience of thy will: that we may in all oure doings, remember our profeſſion and promiſſe, poſſeſſe firme faithe, which truely quieteth and ſetteth at reſt the conſcience of man, feare thy iudgementes, liue vprightly and worthily before thée, glory in the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, ſprinkled and cleanſed
<pb facs="tcp:20797:71"/>with the bloud of thy ſonne Chriſt,<note place="margin">The con mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of a quiet conſcience.</note> enioy peace and true gladneſſe, not troubled inwardly, but ſléepe quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not glorying in the praiſes of men, but reioyce only in thée oure God, in thy mercy and grace, in thy holy truthe, in the price of oure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and in the onely moſte happie ſtate of eternall felicitie, which thou haſte faithfully promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which thy ſonne hathe purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which vnto vs ſhall be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, moſt happely and in due time, thorowe thine onely frée grace and loue towardes vs, in the precious deathe and bloud ſhed of thine only ſonne our alone ſauiour, only aduocate and mediator Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20797:71"/>
               <head>XVI. To haue in remembrance the houre of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Alling to mynde (O eternall god) the fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle ſtate of humain felicitie,<note place="margin">Mans life fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, and but a vayne ſhadow.</note> &amp; the ſwifte paſſage of this bric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle life, how man ſtandeth héere in a vaine ſhadowe, freſhly floriſhing like a floure to day, and can to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe no where be founde, and as quickely forgotten as he is gone: and yéeldeth then vp by the dint of death, his ſwifte paſſage to God or to the Deuill: O how it behooueth vs to ſtartle ſodainely, to beſtirre vs, to looke aboute vs, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſpéedely for ſo ſodayne aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulte? But howe ſhall we Lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:72"/>ſtanding in déede in ſuch infelicitie,<note place="margin">The damnable ſtate of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in thys frayle life.</note> ſlumbring in ſuche ſecuritie, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with frailetie, ſo compaſſed with flatterie, cloked in hipoeriſie, and ouerwhelmed with vanitie, neither yet féele in oure ſelues any fighte or trouble of conſcience, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs as we oughte, for ſo conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niente a tyme? Thou knoweſt (O Lorde) as by thy wrathe we iuſtly alſo féele, howe ſedainly vnwares, death cruelly aſſaileth vs, and ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs from our pleaſures, vayne delectations and deluſious of this deceitfull worlde. We regarde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, the ſodaine comming of the ſonne of man: by whoſe mighty arme (in our forgot fulneſſe) we he woorthily ſtricken to the death, and to our mother the earth againe: in whoſe entrails we were once brod; and oute of whoſe moſte ponſoned pappes, we haue ſuckt the milke, of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20797:72"/>all our deadly delites: and with the bruſting draught of our moſt beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exceſſe, we haue ſodainely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne our ſelues, and haue very willingly faln, vpon thy mercileſſe ſwoorde of deathe. Throughe which iudgement, wort and terrible time,<note place="margin">In what caſe we ſhal ſtande at the houre of death.</note> we ſhall begin then to thinke (with late wailing and wo) far otherwiſe of our formen liues, than we did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the lulling dayes of our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall delices: we ſhall then conſwer the greatneſſe and granitie of, all our affences, and be depely tormon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in vnſufferable anguiſhes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forowes, yelling, lauguiſtying and the auinoſſe, for our careleſſe &amp; moſt graceleſſe negligence: bicauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our health and tune of felicitie, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forgetful of thée, vs we caued not to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte thée, we feared not thy threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vengeance, neither thy Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Prophetes, we were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindefull
<pb facs="tcp:20797:73"/>of the ende, we conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the way of all fleſhe, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred not deathe, neither readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared for his ſodaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming:<note place="margin">The blacke enfine of deth diſplayed.</note> whoſe enſigne by thy iuſtice, is openly all blacke diſplayed, moſt ougly iſſuing out of his darke ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, to the ſpéedie deſtruction of all fleſhe. Therefore (O Lord) as oure liues are wholely in. thyne onely hande, and are by thée (when we call vppon thée) moſt graciouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: quicken our harts to prayer, endue vs thorowe thy grace, wyth thine heauenly wiſdome, teache vs thereby to number our dayes, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie oure hartes vnto wiſedome, to be mindefull of thée our God, not to be forgetfull of oure wretched and wicked ſtate, and to remember al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thy rightful iuſtice in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente: that we may endeuor to be ſuche in déede in oure liues, as we
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20797:73"/>woulde wiſhe moſte gladly to be founde at our deathes. O heauenly father, ſo ſtrengthen vs with thy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall and woonted grace, that as we may haue this worlde in moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt contempte: ſo we may alſo as effectually craue at thine holy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the daily proſpering and going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in vertue: pray, that our loue may abounde towardes godly diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for the fourme of good liuing:<note place="margin">Diſcipline worketh the fourme of good liuing.</note> yéelde fréely forth the frutes of ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and true repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: haue ready and preſt wils to ſhewe true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bothe in body and ſoule: to be humble and méeke in ſpirite: not to ſtay at any time the deniall of oure ſelues: to ſubiecte our ſelues to thy holy will and commaundements: and ſo to leane gladly to the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this worldes calamities: not for oure ſelues, but for the loue of Ieſus Chriſte, &amp; for our brethren
<pb facs="tcp:20797:74"/>(for ſo ſhal we be knowne to be the children of God.) All which, if we happely poſſeſſe, vſe, and put in dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe:<note place="margin">The ſweete frutes of good lyfe agaynſt the comming of death.</note> great ſhall be the cauſe of oure ioy, to haue good affiaunce in thy mercy, a ſwéete taſt of good life, and a ſure hope by happie death: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming in the meane while, pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Pilgrims in ſpirituall pouertie, and not regarding the pleaſures of this life: that oure ſoules may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the felicitie of thy freedome: be daily lifted vp vnto thée in this our ſhort race: that we may continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praie, with ſorowfull ſighings, déepe ſobbings, inwarde gronings, and ſhedding ſalte teares in our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed and moſte humble ſutes, bewayling oure miſerable ſtate, mourning the delay of this bodyes diſſolution, and yéeld with pacience to abide the ſtroke of deathe, that when it, which is the laſte enemie,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20797:74"/>ſhall be deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Paciente aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of death, bringeth the ſoule to reſt.</note> our ſpirites may haue reſt in thine eternall life: the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the only merites of thy ſonne, our Lord and ſauior Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII. To haue in remembrance the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete iudgementes of God, and to feare the withdrawing of his grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing good expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by thyne holy ſcriptures (O thou rightuous God) that as thou arte moſte high, moſt glorious, moſt holy,<note place="margin">The maieſtie and great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God ouer al fleſh.</note> wiſe and mighty, and a great God aboue all Gods, eternal, and from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: ſo arte thou alſo a Lord, a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, a maſter, an ouerſcer &amp; a iudge ouer all the dooings of men, yea, a ſeuere iudge, a ſtraighte examiner, an vpright &amp; iuſt rewarder: againſt
<pb facs="tcp:20797:75"/>whome, no man may once rowſe or aduaunce him ſelfe, ſtande in his owne conceite, or ſhewe before thée any proude or hautie countinance: for it is thou onely (O Lorde) that art omnipotent, whoſe mighty arm reacheth ouer all: which aduanceſt and bringeſt lowe, which ſtrykeſt and healeſt, which woundeſt and makeſt whole, which lifteſt vp and throweſt downe againe, which dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in thy iudgement, not after the manner of men, wickedly winking at the ſinnes, generally committed of all, or of a few: but vſeſt vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto all withoute reſpecte of perſons: generally, particularly, to many, to a fewe, and to ſome one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, when their ſinnes before thée are ful, and waxeth ripe vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, apte to fall, and ready to féele from thy wrathfull hande, the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine ſtroke of thy vengeance: for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20797:75"/>vengeance (annexed to thy power) is only thine and thy iuſt rewarde:<note place="margin">God a God of vengeance.</note> whoſe iudgementes for ſinne, are very terrible, fierce, a flaming and conſuming fire, to licke vp, catche, burne and deuonre, all or ſome, as the cauſe ſhal require, and as by thy iuſtice in iudgement thou finedeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (for ſo in all ages, we haue both truly heard and knowne) which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of thine (in ſundry wiſe) are all wrytten for our vnderſtanding and learning,<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to be remebred, and why.</note> always to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of vs, to put vs in good mind, to terrifie vs, to bridle oure affections, to feare thy maieſtie, to ſéeke the true knowledge of thy will, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently therein to obey thée, and to eſcape aptly therby thy iuſt rigor &amp; vengeance, for vengeance is thine, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt reward, O holy and iuſt god, which alſo artmoſt gracious, which ſpareſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we deſerue puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:76"/>in thy wrath thinkeſt vpon mercy, and haſte vowed compaſſion vpon the poore penitent, haue mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me moſte wretched ſinner: O forgéeue me all my wickedneſſe paſt, let thy tender mercie preuent my ſinnes, caſt them al behinde thy backe, and ſhewe me againe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable countinance: for my ſinnes ſore trouble me, they iuſtly accuſe me, thy iudgementes terribly thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt me, they ſore ſhake my limmes with feare and trembling, and terrifie out of meaſure, my ſore vexed and contrite heart. And if by thine heauenly motion (O Lorde) I yet wade further in thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and conſider the very heauens,<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dring.</note> not to be cleane in thy ſight, but expecte the day of their renouation, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cleereneſſe and puritie: O how am I occaſioned to be the more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, and to bewail my wretched
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20797:76"/>ſtate, in the lothſomneſſe of my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.<note place="margin">The heauens, the Angelles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and the ſtars falne from heauen, are all ſubject to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of god.</note> And if in the Angels them ſelues thou haſte founde ſinne, and the deſert of eternall death, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſpared thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ouer them, O what ſhall become of me, earthie, fraile, and moſte ſinnefull wretche? And if alſo the gloryous ſtarres themſelues, haue in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of their outwarde cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and beautie, falne down from heauen, &amp; abide likewiſe thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: what ſhall I a maſſe of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtime and filthe of the earthe, looke for at thy wrathfull hand, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing my very ſecrete ſinnes not hid from thee, in their moſte horrible, lothſome, and poyſoned apperance? But yet I beſéeche thée (O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father) althoughe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be a ſtraighte iudge ouer all thy creatures for ſin, whether of heauen or of earth, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall, terreſtriall or infernall, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte
<pb facs="tcp:20797:77"/>to thy will, and to abide iuſtly thy iudgement: for thine approued clemencies ſake, and tender pity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me, imprinted ſtil freſhe in my memorie, and boldened thereby to approche thy preſence, ſo to exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me thy great mercy and grace, that as I nowe craue the continual good motion &amp; inward ſtirring vp of my mind by thine holy ſpirit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member always the burthen of my ſinne, and to feare the terror of thy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for due puniſhing of the ſame: ſo I make vnto thée moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſute, not to be deſtitute of a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith, true truſt and confidence in thy mercy and grace, that thou wilt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble my ſoule before thée, prepare in me a cleane heart, and a will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineable to thy teſtimonyes: that how ſo euer by thy will and iuſtice, I féele in this worlde for good thy priuate iudgements, to the purging,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20797:77"/>repreſſing, and kéeping vnder, my ſtubburne and proude fleſhe:<note place="margin">God at the laſt day by his iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, rendereth full payment vnto all wicked ſinners.</note> at the generall iudgement day, and in the world to come, that when al works good and bad, ſhal be reduced to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and when a ſtraight accompt and reckening ſhall be made, and a iuſt rewarde giuen, celeſtiall or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal both to body and ſoul. I may yet eſcape the fulneſſe of thy paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t due for euer to the wicked, by theyr deadly and iuſte deſerte. Heare me (O my God of all mercie) and take thou care ouer me this day, moſte graciouſly directe me, confirme and ſtrengthen me in thy wayes, leaſte in mine owne reſpecte I be founde but féeble, and weake, ſlipping, full of inconſtancie, vncleane and too too filthie: for there is no will, no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, nor holyneſſe that auayleth, no wiſedome, no temperaunce, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, loue, dilygence, chaſtitie,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:78"/>or mine owne keping to good effect, without the frée direction of thyne holy hand, daily gouernment, moſt gratious preſeruation,<note place="margin">God freely by his grace dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth to good life.</note> defending &amp; holy watching. All which, as they procéede onely from thée, and are of thy méere mercie beſtowed moſte bountifully vpon me: ſo graunt me grace, (yea the continuaunce of thy grace) not to be forgetfull of thée, but always to remember thée with al humilitie and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulneſſe, euch from the very depth and bottome of mine harte and ſoule, all the dayes of my life, and haue thenceforth the rewarde of eternall felicitie: tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thy mercie, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merites of thy ſonne and my Sauioure Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:20797:78"/>
               <head>XVIII. The Flighte of the faithfull Soule to Chriſte, in the exuemitie of temptations, and invvarde affections of the minde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I, in preſenting my ſelfe before thée (O ſwéete Ieſu my Lord and only ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure) ſhall ſéeme by thy gratious permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſome thing to ſay vnto thée, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heauineſſe of harte for my ſinnes, which are infinite moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable by inſtice in thy ſight, and moſt plainly alſo proue by thy woorde of truthe, that thou art yet bounde to be fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vnto me: bound to caſt all my ſinnes behinde thy backe: bounde to beſtowe thy good graces, thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and beneſites vpon me: yea, and bounde alſo in time, to giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me thine heauenly and celeſtiall Paradiſe: I will not do it raſhly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:20797:79"/>thée (my Lorde and my God) vpon preſumption, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or for that I beare not a due and woorthy reuerence vnto the glory of thy diuine maieſtie: neither meane I therby (in any thing) to diminiſh the excellencie of thyne heauenly power: but rather to magnifie and extoll thine only omnipotencie and great goodneſſe, and to ſtirre vp my ſelfe (euen with al humilitie) to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in parte, the deare loue that thou beareſt towardes me thy moſt euil and vnprofitable ſeruaunte. O my ſwéete Ieſu,<note place="margin">Chriſt is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged, and why?</note> beare nowe with me therfore, and firſt of all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I beſeeche thée, thy perfecte knowledge héerin, that thine eterns and moſt mercifull father, did ſend thée into this worlde and vale of great miſerie, to the ende thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſaue me, comfort me in my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, ſtrengthen me, defende and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20797:79"/>deliuer me moſte wretched ſinner, in all anguiſhes, troubles, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and miſeries, bothe of bodie and ſoule, and that my ſinnes ſhuld not preuaile againſte me, when I humbly pray and craue thy mercie.<note place="margin">Chriſtes obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience to hys father, for hys flocke.</note> Thou (O mercyfull and louyng Lorde and ſauior) was obedient to the will of thine heauenly father, like a moſt lowly and mild childe: and for the loue ſake alſo whiche thou hadſt to thy flocke, like a moſt deare louing paſtoure, diddeſt offer thy ſelfe to die, euen the moſt cruell and ſhameful death vpon the croſſe. And alſo, if in caſe I did at any time make reſiſtaunce, rebelliouſly and wickedly to diſobey, to ſtraggle, or ſtray abrode when thou calledſte vnto me, tourning the deafe eare, would not heart thée: he ſtraighte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly charged thée, and gaue expreſſe Commaundemente vnto thée alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:20797:80"/>that thou ſhouldeſt conſtraine and compell me home again to the fold: and to be alſo his beloued gheſt in his heauenly kingdome, at the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of thy mariage.<note place="margin">The cauſe of chriſts death.</note> O Chriſte, for this onely good purpoſe, was thou borne vnto vs: for thys cauſe didſte thou humble thy ſelfe among vs: and for thys moſte happie ende, did thy father ſo plentifully enrich thée, and euen filled thée with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of his good giftes &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Therefore, O my mercifull Lorde Ieſu, remember I pray thée thy tharge, ſée thou be mindefull of thy good and moſt holy office: and yeeld héerein to the obedience of thy fathers will, as thou arte bound and woonte to doe.<note place="margin">The bonde of the wealthy in this world</note> Thou knoweſt (O Lord) that all good and iuſt lawes, binde thoſe that be riche &amp; wealthy in this world, to diſtribute parte of their ſubſtance, to the relieuement
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20797:80"/>of poore and néedie perſonnes: yea, and the richer they be of the good gifts of God, and in the greater mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries they finde their poore &amp; néedy neighbors, the more are they bound gladly to helpe and ſuccoure them.<note place="margin">Chriſt aboun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riches, cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titie, power, and loyes in comparable.</note> This I ſay lord, bicauſe I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thée to be moſte riche, and of moſte excellent power, abounding farre aboue all others, in all ioyes and treaſures incomparable: where I contrarywiſe, am in greate ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and heauineſſe of hart,<note place="margin">The diſtreſſed loule.</note> oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with all care and miſerie, and with extréeme pouertie and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie both of body and ſoule. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lord) I humbly make ſute vnto thée,<note place="margin">Chriſt humbly chalenged.</note> &amp; chalenge thée to be my ſpéedie helper, for that I know thée to be moſte readye, moſte willing, moſt able, and moſt bound to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me. And thoughe I haue moſte gréeuouſly offended the eyes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:20797:81"/>maieſtie, yet bicauſe thou art mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful (and I appealing to thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) thou canſt not ſet thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt me,<note place="margin">Chryſt bound to helpe, and why.</note> or withholde thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion from me, but arte rather bound with all good incoragement ſpéedily to helpe &amp; ſuccour me. And why Lord ſhould I ſay this? truly for this cauſe, the greter (in the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellency of thy holy ſtate) thou doſt approuedly find thy ſelfe aboue all other: ſo muche the more art thou ſubiecte and obedient to the indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable law of charitie, and to be therfore moſt mercifull vnto me: and to be obedient thervnto, is the greateſt and moſte porfecte ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raintie, thou ſhouldeſt not be that Chryſt of God, onleſſe thou diddeſt gladly participate thy deare loue to thy brethren. Yea, I ſay moreouer thou art ſo much the rather bound to loue me, for that thou arte myne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20797:81"/>head, and I the meaner parte and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ver of thy body. Neither maieſt thou ſay, thou canſt not helpe me:<note place="margin">Chryſte the head and cow fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er of hys members.</note> for although with the flowing fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of thy grace, thou haſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully enriched all the Sainctes that euer wer from the beginning: yet notwithſtanding that, thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine treaſures are not ſo ſpente, nether ſodiminiſhed, but that there remayneth ſtore abundauntly for me,<note place="margin">Store remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Gods grace.</note> and for all penitent ſinners. No no Lorde, thou haſt treaſures yet ſuperfluous, which ſhal endure for euer: and wilt not thou aide and comforte me thy poore &amp; wretched creature with the crums that fall from thy table, for my moſt ioyful refection ſeeing me now in danger &amp; irke to periſh?<note place="margin">The aſſured fayth of the thirſten ſoule.</note> Shat I thinke (O Lord) thy compaſſion ſo ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der and ſo farre from me, that I ſhal doubt to be refreſhed at thy gracious ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d?
<pb facs="tcp:20797:82"/>No, God forbid, I wil neuer thinke ſo euill or ſlenderly of thee, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beléeue, that as thou arte able, ſo thou wilt in déede helpe me, and am thorowly perſuaded whie. Am not I (ſwéete Ieſu) one of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious redéemed Iewelles? And haſt thou not ſpent,<note place="margin">Fayth in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloud.</note> euen thy moſte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious heart bloud for me, ſuffering for my ſake, ſo many &amp; ſo extreame paines &amp; moſte greeuous torments? Yea, and haſte thou not giuen thine owne deare life and ſoule, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe me vnto thy ſelfe, and to liue with thée in thy fathers kingdome. And nowe to relieue or recouer me out of daunger, ſhouldeſt thou ſhew thy ſelfe ſo vnkinde vnto me, that I can not be partaker of thy ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtore, thine ouerplus and thine offalles? Thy father did ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enriche thée, with ſo many his woorthy graces, to the end, thou (O
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20797:82"/>Lord) ſhuldeſt behold in this world the ſickneſſe and great neceſſities of thy troubled flocke, and largely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to diſtribute vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their pouertie, and to eaſe them alſo of their painefulneſſe and infirmitie. And bicauſe (O my Lord and ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure) I yéelde and humbly confeſſe me, to be one of thoſe poore, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; ſcabbed ſhéepe: and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thée alſo, the only bountifull,<note place="margin">Scabde ſhepe.</note> good and free phiſition: I come ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore boldly, and ſay thus vnto thée:<note place="margin">Chryſt the phiſitian.</note> O Chriſt Ieſu, as thy mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath fréely giuen thée vnto me, with the fulneſſe of thine incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and heauenly treaſures, for my ready health, wealth &amp; ſtrength both of body and ſoule: ſo I now flée vnto thée, moſte toyfully embraſing thée, and in ſuche wiſe truſte in thy mercy, that thou ſhalt too too muche wrong me, if thou ſtóc from me or
<pb facs="tcp:20797:83"/>forſake me. Yea Lorde, I ſay vnto thée, in conſideration hereof, thou oughteſt not, neither canſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banbon or caſt me out from thee, but retaine &amp; embrace me, for my moſt ioyful &amp; ſauing health. O Lord Ieſu, ſuffer me yet a litle to queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thée: Was not thou the very ſame man,<note place="margin">Chriſt humbly chalenged.</note> the ſame Lorde, ſauiour &amp; god, which by fauour, hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched thine holy Apoſtles, gaueſt them alſo in charge, that they ſhuld communicate, deale and deuide to others ſuch ſpirituall ryches &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſures, as thou before haddeſt giuen vnto them. Should, I iudge of thée that giueſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente to others in dooing good things, that thou thy ſelfe wilte not perfourme the ſame? O Lord, as thou art a god of mercy &amp; truth, and delighteſt of all men to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo noted, were it poſſible for thée
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20797:83"/>to alter one iot of thy puritie, moſt perfect &amp; beautiful clereneſſe of thy godly &amp; diuine nature, wherby one ſhéepe of thy flock ſhould quayle or find any light occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of offence? O Ieſu, as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art righteous, ſo art not thou a ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling block vnto the righ teous.<note place="margin">Strong faythe in Chryſte.</note> And truly my ſoule truſteth in thée: it mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth vp into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s before thée, &amp; my faith is liuely towards thee. O performe therfore faythfully towards me (as thou art faithful) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thou didſt ſo iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund vnto thine Apoſtles and to vs. Thou certainly doeſt know that thine heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father (at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) filled thée withal vertues, ſtuffed thée with al treſures, poured his graces vpon thée with al plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe: to the ende that in thys world thou ſhouldeſt not bend nor ſet thy mind, properly to poſſeſſe &amp; gather treaſure for thine own ſelf:
<pb facs="tcp:20797:84"/>but that thou ſhouldeſt altogither, turne and apply thine endeuoure, to ſée me and the reſt of thy poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren comforted, ſafely nouriſhed, kept, ſtrengthened and defended in all aſſayes. And ſo thou haſte done hitherto,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> as S. Paule beareth vs in hande: for all that thou haſt preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, wrought and ſuffered from the beginning,<note place="margin">Chryſts incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; ſo forth, are al chalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the faithfull ſoule as his owne.</note> was for me, for thine, and my brethrens ſake. Thine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incarnation therefore, thy natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and circumciſion, thy baptiſme, thy faſting and praying, thy temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, thy watchings, thy prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, thy painful trauellings and dangers, thy ſhameleſſe accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſpittings and raylings, thy bloudie ſweat, thy woful and bitter teares, thy cruel and traiterous apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, thy croſſe and moſte painefull paſſion, thy bloud ſhed, thy life, thy death, thy buriall, thy reſurrection,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20797:84"/>yea &amp; thy moſte glorious aſcention, into euerlaſting life, and al the reſt which thou haſte done, felt, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, was all for me, they are all mine, and I now chalenge them all at thine hand, as mine owne. Al thy diuine treaſures are mine: yea, and euen thou thy ſelfe art wholely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo mine,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Thy father hath giuen thée vnto me, and thou alſo was conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that I ſhould poſſeſſe thée, and therfore thou canſt not nowe denie thy ſelfe to be mine.<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> Thou cameſt into this worlde to take paynes for me, and to ſerue me: and doſte thou not knowe, that what ſo euer the ſeruaunt getteth by his trauaile, he gaineth it, not for him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Chryſt a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt.</note> but for the vſe of hym whome he ſerueth. Thou didſt like a puiſſant Prince, triumphantly fighte for me,<note place="margin">Chryſt a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour.</note> by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and winning battail: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the treaſures and ſpoyles, the
<pb facs="tcp:20797:85"/>triumphs and victories, which thou then didſt get, are altogither mine. It is not now of late O Ieſu, (thou moſte victorious and noble Prince) ſince thou, as with whom were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lefte theſe greate and precious treaſures: and haſte thou nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed them all? I will not ſay thine, but my treaſures: wherewith thou haſt purchaſed for me a moſte pleaſant place of reſt, euen the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and heauenly Paradiſe?<note place="margin">Paradiſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by Chriſte.</note> yea, thou haſte alſo taken poſſeſſion of it for me: and ſhouldeſt thou now goe aboute to diſpoſſeſſe me of myne owne, and to depriue me of mine inheritaunce and right? No Lorde no, there is in me no poſſibilitie at all to beléeue that:<note place="margin">Experience of Chriſtes good nature, and his mercie.</note> for I haue (in ſuche wiſe) bothe hearde, felte, and knowne, diuerſly and innumerable wayes, of thy gratious good nature, and of thy perfecte charitie and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20797:85"/>truthe, that I muſte néedes confeſſe thy great goodneſſe and liberalitie towardes me, and ſo to truſt truely in thee. Thou haſt diligently ſought for me, thou haſte offered thy ſelfe vnto me, thou haſt ſo many wayes called vnto me, and ſo diuers and ſundry wayes allured me to come to thy moſte royal and magnificent marriage, promiſing to accepte me, for thy deare beloued gheaſt:<note place="margin">Math. xj. xxij.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I am moſte certainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded and fully aſſured, not to be deceiued of thée. And thou haſt ſayd: he that commeth to thée,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6</note> thou wilte not caſt him oute.</p>
               <p>And nowe that I moſte gladly and willingly yéelde vnto thee, and of, good heart come towardes thée, wilt thou turne thy face away from me, and not cheare me with thy comfortable &amp; ſwéete countenance? As I am conſtrained, and by thy
<pb facs="tcp:20797:86"/>ſwéete allurementes perſuaded, or rather enforced (beholdyng myne owne imperfection) to come vnto thée, that arte altogither perfecte: euen ſo arte thou (by thy large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes) bounde to accept me. Thou diddeſt ſay:<note place="margin">Ioho. 12.</note> If I ſhall once be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I will then braw all things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. Thine exaltation vppon the croſſe (O Lord) hath bene (as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue) long ſince perfourmed, as alſo thy riſing againe from deathe, and thine aftention into heauen. Theſe things therefore, thus truly of thée performed and finiſhed, I requyre thee (O Ieſu) to draw me vnto thée, as thou by thy promiſſe arte moſte iuſtly bounde. I knowe thou arte not angrie, or (at the leaſte) not at deſtance with me: for ſeeing thou haſte commaunded me, that I be not at hatred with mine enemie: I can not doubt, but that thou thy ſelf
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20797:86"/>alſo, kéepeſt truely this thy ſwéete commaundement: and ſo much the rather to be perfourmed of thée, as thou arte more able than I, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the vſe of charitie. Thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not ſay, that thou art not bounde to loue me, alleaging that I am thine ennemie,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> or that I haue done thée manifolde iniuries (which I muſte needes moſte truely confeſſe:) for if by thy precept of charitie, thou haſt ſtraightly bounde me to loue myne enemies, to doe them good, to helpe them in their néede, and to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for them: I know right wel that in thus doing, thou arte muche more bounde than I. Wherefore, if thou wilt not loue me as thy frend, loue me yet (at the leaſte) as thyne enemie doe me good, help me in my neceſſities, and pray to thine heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father for me, as thou art in dede moſte bound to doe. I doe aſſuredly
<pb facs="tcp:20797:87"/>know, that thy vertue, thy goodnes, and thine heauenly charitie is not ſo ſmall, nor ſo ſtenderly planted in thée, that it will ſuffer it ſelfe to be ouercome of mine extreme vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or naughtineſſe: no, how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo euer it aboundeth.<note place="margin">Roma. 1.</note> Thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement chargeth me, that I (in any wiſe) ſuffer not my ſelfe to be vanquiſhed, by the malice of my enemies: and wilte thou ſuffer thy ſolfe to be ouercome, by my diffrét<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; leudneſſe. This verily hathe no likeneſſe of truth in it. Thou haſt taught and commaunded me, that I with doing good to mine enemies, do ouercome and va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſh their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: and I then require thée (O my mercifull Lord and onely ſauicure) that thou alſo thy ſelfe, obſerue this diuine precept and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God thy father, as thy godly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bindeth thée. Paie thy debte I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20797:87"/>pray thée: that is,<note place="margin">Chriſtes pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and howe.</note> vanquiſh my vain ſtoutneſſe, my wickedneſſe &amp; great malice, with the vertue of gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and with thy moſt bounteous and plentifull goodneſſe. And if I haue an harte before thée, hardened as the Adamant rock or Diamond: breake it then or mollifie it (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee) with the piercing moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of thy moſte pretious bloude: O ſtéepe mine heart well therein, ſouple it, make it ſofte, and temper it with the moiſture of thy grace. O lette thy Spirite then for euer poſſeſſe me, henceforthe aſſiſte me, and be my moſte gratious and good guide, that I may vntill the ende, obey thy moſte holy wil. O woorke mine harte a newe, after thine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed manner, and according to thy good promiſſes of olde.</p>
               <p>And if thou anſweare,<note place="margin">Ezech 16.</note> that thou haſt many times mercifully for giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20797:88"/>me:<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> and that thou therefore wilte looke no more vppon me, or harken to my ſute. I anſwere: If thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt Peter in commaundemente,<note place="margin">Math 18.</note> that he ſhould pardon his enemies, not ſeuen times onely, but ſeuentie times ſeuen times: that is alwayes, and as often as they ſhall offende him: It foloweth then, that thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo arte ſo muche the more bounde héerein than I, for as much as thou doſte excéede me and all men, in all charitie: and ſpecially, bicauſe that I haue ſinned,<note place="margin">Sinne of Gods electe.</note> not of any deadely malice, but thorowe ignorance and frailtie, and for that bothe I and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſawe not rightly the maieſtie of him, whome we ſo offended, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coulde we make a right viewe of the goodes which we did loſe, nor of the euils, in which we daily did incurre. But thou peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture wilt yet ſay: I haue giuen thée ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20797:88"/>of lighte and true doctrine, by ſending my faithfull preachers and miniſters theſe many yeres vnto thée, that thou art now without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and thy faulte inexcuſable. Agaynſt this doo I yet replie: that euen to the Iewes (thy peculier people) thou gauoſt ſuche lights to ſée, and ſuch knowledge to perceiue what thou was, that they were yet inexcuſable, as thou thy ſelfe dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſay. And notwithſtanding this,<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> thou beeing in triumphe vppon the Croſſe, diddeſt make their excuſe, and prayed for them, ſaying: that in putting thée to that cruell death, they knew not what they dyd. In conſideration of which things, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou art myne onely aduocate, myne onely Sauiour,<note place="margin">Chryſte the onely ſauiour, the onely ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocate.</note> my God and dearely beloued of thy father, my truſt is in thée, that thou wilt haue mercy vppon me, and pray for me.
<pb facs="tcp:20797:89"/>O pray for me therefore I beſéeche thee, make myne excuſe to thyne and myne heauenly father: O ſaue thou me, and then ſhall I bée ſafe. And if thou wilte yet lay to my charge (O thou iuſte God) that I haue with earneſt ſtoutneſſe and rebellion offended thée: myne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere agayne vnto thée is (whych ſéeſt the ſecrotes of myne hearte) that in ſo dooing I haue doone it, not wilfully and of malice, but rather of frayltie, or through feruencie of zeale, with all ſingleneſſe of heart, to ſeeke onely thy glory. Wherein through wante of knowledge, and the true lighte of thy holy Coſpell, I haue diſobediently and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed iniquitie: but yet, not in ſuthe wyſe as doth the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reprobate, fixedly, of wylfull malice,<note place="margin">Sinne of the reprobate.</note> or as an hater of thée: who by all poſſible meanes ſéeketh thy
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20797:89"/>diſhonour, and falleth with al grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyneſſe from iniquitie to iniquitie. Therefore I doubte not but ſuche zeale or frayletie ioyned with ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleneſſe, is pardonable before thée, through the gretneſſe of thy mercy: yea, it is ſo much the more to the furtherance of thy glory (o Chriſt) rather than the only offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of meere ſimplicitie, when the largeneſſe of thy mercyes ſo bountifully floweth from thee. Yea, and I know aſſuredly, that throgh thy goodneſſe and feruent charitie, thou act inforced to vanquiſhe and vtterly ouerthrow my weakeneſſe, wickeoneſſe, malice and blindneſſe, euen to the pardoning of all (from the firſte to the laſte) that hathe beene amiſſe. For if the iuſte bloud of Abell called to God for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce agaynſt his brother to hys condemnation, and preuayled,<note place="margin">The bloud of Abel cried for vengeance.</note> I
<pb facs="tcp:20797:90"/>know that thy bloud muche more effectually calleth to ſaluation:<note place="margin">Chryſtes bloud calleth to ſaluation.</note> and calling, obteineth aboundaunce of Gods mercies for me. Saue me therefore (O my Lorde and ſwéete Ieſu) according to thy promyſes and bonde of great charitie: againſt the whiche, neither thou oughteſt nor canſt reſiſte. O ſaue me I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche thée, and take me to thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſometune one of thy great eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, very wicked, very faithleſſe, obſtinate, headie and rebellious: but nowe thy louing brother, thy faythfull frende, thyne obediente louer, and a ſounde member of thy body. O ſaue me then I ſay, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte my ſoule, guyde mée in thy wayes, ſtrengthen mée, and let not thy ſpirite departe from mee, that I may hencefoorthe ioyfully pleaſe thée, and render alwayes vnto thy father (through thée) all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20797:90"/>due prayſe, honour, and glory, here in thys vale of myſerie, and in the euerlaſting world which is to come. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Henry Bynneman, for William Norton. ANNO. 1572.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
